<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon of the true, spiritual transubstantiation, oppos'd to the gross, carnal, imaginary transubstantiation wherein the true meaning of the Lord's Supper is opened, in order to a constant, habitual and actual preparation to it / by Beverley.</title>
            <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27625</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2175</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18401</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12258072</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12258072</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57608</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27625)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57608)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 167:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon of the true, spiritual transubstantiation, oppos'd to the gross, carnal, imaginary transubstantiation wherein the true meaning of the Lord's Supper is opened, in order to a constant, habitual and actual preparation to it / by Beverley.</title>
                  <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 56.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57608:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57608:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> SERMON Of the True, Spiritual, Tranſubſtantiation, Oppos'd to the GROSS, CARNAL, IMAGINARY, Tranſubſtantiation.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN The true Meaning of the <hi>Lord's Supper</hi> is opened, in order to a conſtant, habitual, and actual Preparation to it.</p>
            <p>By <hi>T Beverley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for the Author, 1687.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:57608:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:57608:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Chriſtian Readers, ESPECIALLY MY CONTINUAL AUDITORS.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Offer this Sermon to the Publick, as the most ſatisfactory Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution concerning the Lord's Supper and its true Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, in oppoſition to the falſe, ſo eagerly contended: I have done it with all the Modeſty and Inoffenſiveneſs I could, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Injury to Truth, without <hi>Denying Chriſt before Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have put the best Value, and all the Value poſſible, upon <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation;</hi> that is, To Interpret it into a True Scripture, Goſpel No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, into a Spirituality: I confeſs the very Word, nor any one Word parallel to it is found, that I know of, in the <hi>New Teſtament;</hi> but the Thing it ſelf is every where in the Goſpel of Christ: <hi>Chriſt in us,</hi> and <hi>we in Chriſt, Baptiz'd into one Body, one Body, one Bread, a Drinking into one Spirit,</hi> are favourable to it; Chriſt being <hi>All</hi> in <hi>All</hi> the <hi>Head, putting on Chriſt,</hi> but above all, <hi>dwelling in Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt dwelling in us,</hi> joyn'd with <hi>Eating his Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>Drinking his Blood,</hi> are the very ſame thing with this <hi>Spiritual Tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation;</hi> to which the <hi>Bread and Wine</hi> are the moſt fit and ſenſible Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bols, and Chriſt is as really preſent in them by his Word, ſanctifying them into Spirituality, as in his Word it ſelf; And <hi>if we Abide in him,</hi> and <hi>his Words abide in us,</hi> we are one with him in Both, as <hi>the Vine and the Branches are one,</hi> John 15. 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I conſider nothing is ſo likely to ſatisfie ſo deeply an engraven Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in ſome mens minds, as this true and faithful Account of it, as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:57608:3"/> could ſatisfie the confuſed Lineaments of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar's Dream</hi> in his own mind, but <hi>Daniel's Prophetical Revelation of the Thing,</hi> and of the Truth it ſelf to him. I look upon this True Preſence of Chriſt given from the Word of God, as the moſt effectual means to recover thoſe to the Truth who <hi>live in Error</hi> concerning it, to ſettle the Wavering, reſolve the Doubtful, to confirm and ſtabliſh in the one <hi>Truth</hi> always <hi>preſent,</hi> the True Chriſtian. This is far above all Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Philoſophy, Vindication from Antiquity, and the Fathers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it. When we find we have that which anſwers all the Notions of Scripture, and is worthy to be its meaning, we may be at reſt. Here the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> Zeal for a <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> the <hi>Lutherans</hi> for a <hi>Conſubſtantiation, other Proteſtants for a real Preſence,</hi> may find full Reception and juſt Entertainment, in a ſenſe worthy of them if they will accept it.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, I have aimed at poſſeſſing the Minds of Chriſtians with ſo high a ſpiritual Notion, to recommend the <hi>Goſpel</hi> as Preach'd, as in the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> in its higheſt Intendments and Efficacy, and to win mens Souls to the outward Obſervation by their being impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the inward Life and Power; In which Purſuit many excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Truths, and of great moment, have riſen up, and offered themſelves. There remains nothing, but to beſeech the God of all Grace to give his Bleſſing to it, and to you particularly, My very Honoured and truly Loved Hearers, to whom it is my conſtant Endeavour, through the Grace of God, to open to you together the Spirituality and the Reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nableneſs of Divine Things; whom I commend to God and the Word of his Grace, to build you up, ſtrengthen, ſtabliſh, ſettle you, and ſhall thereunto labour while God allows me opportunity, with moſt conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Meditations, moſt earneſt Prayers, and deareſt Affections.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very faithful Servant in the Work of the Lord, <hi>Beverley.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:57608:3"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS OF THE SERMON.</head>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>AN Introduction upon the general view of the Inſtitution of the Lord's Supper, as given by three Evangeliſts, and by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> as a fourth, compos'd into a Harmony; and our Lord's Diſcourſe, <hi>John</hi> 6. lying as a Foundation, <hi>Page</hi> 1. <hi>to Page</hi> 5.</item>
                  <item>General Obſervations upon the Harmony, giving Advantage to the right underſtanding the Inſtitution, <hi>p.</hi> 6. <hi>to p.</hi> 9.</item>
                  <item>The method of the Sermon is laid down in general, <hi>p.</hi> 9.</item>
                  <item>The firſt general Head ſhews, How Christ gives his Body or his Fleſh to eat, and his Blood to drink, in four Points, <hi>p.</hi> 10.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Point</hi> 1. The Humane Nature of Christ is in ſacred Writ moſt expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively ſet out by his Fleſh, his Body, and his Blood, <hi>p.</hi> 11, 12, 13.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Point</hi> 2. The Fleſh, Body, and Blood of Chriſt, and all his Actions therein, are as ſo many Preparations, that he may be ſpiritually eaten and drunk, <hi>p.</hi> 14.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Point</hi> 3. The Humane Nature of Christ, and all his Sufferings and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in it, are ſo many Reſts and Repoſitories of the Divine Power, <hi>p.</hi> 14, 15, 16:</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Point</hi> 4. The Divine Power of the Son of God extends the Body and Blood of Christ, his Action and ſuffering therein in their ſaving virtue,
<pb facs="tcp:57608:4"/> without limitation to Time or Place. This is branch'd into three Points, <hi>p.</hi> 17.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Point</hi> 1. The Divine Nature of the Son of God, acting in the Humane Nature united to him, can draw out ſuch ſpiritual Efficacies from his Actions and Sufferings therein, as ſhall be moſt conducive to the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Souls that believe in him: and this is diſplay'd briefly in ſome Reſemblances of Nature, though found inſufficient to decipher ſo great a Myſtery, <hi>p.</hi> 17, 18.</item>
                  <item>Therefore theſe Efficacies are drawn out into four Cauſalities according to Scripture,
<list>
                        <item>1. Of an eternal, propitiatory, expiatory Cauſe, <hi>p.</hi> 19.</item>
                        <item>2. Of an exemplar Cauſe, <hi>p.</hi> 20.</item>
                        <item>3. Of an efficient, unitive Cauſe, <hi>p.</hi> 22.</item>
                        <item>4. Of an argumentative Cauſe, fill'd alſo with divine Efficacy, <hi>p.</hi> 23. <hi>to p.</hi> 26.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Point</hi> 2. <hi>and</hi> 3. The Divine Efficacy of Christ cannot be hindered by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance either of Time or Place, <hi>p.</hi> 27, 28.</item>
                  <item>General Head the ſecond, propounds to ſhew how clear the Paſſage is to thoſe Words, <hi>Take, Eat, &amp;c.</hi> from the Point of Chriſt giving his Fleſh to eat; by ſhewing, That as there is a rich Communicativeneſs on the part of Christ, giving his Fleſh to eat, and his Blood to drink, ſo there are receiving Faculties and Powers of Man, fitted by Grace, that may be truly ſaid, in a ſpiritual ſenſe, to eat and to drink, as Chriſt is ſaid to give, <hi>p.</hi> 29, 30.</item>
                  <item>This Eating is therefore reſembled with eating and drinking,
<list>
                        <item>1. As in pledge of Peace and Reconciliation with God, <hi>p.</hi> 31.</item>
                        <item>2. As a ſolemn Act of Worſhip, <hi>p.</hi> 32.</item>
                        <item>3. As Eating and Drinking is made a Symbol of Eternal Glory, <hi>p.</hi> 32.</item>
                        <item>4. Principally as Eating and Drinking are in order to Life and Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment; where the Notion of Tranſubſtantiation hath its moſt
<pb facs="tcp:57608:4"/> proper place, and is moſt fully diſcours'd in its spiritual ſenſe. <hi>p.</hi> 32. <hi>to the end of p.</hi> 38.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>General Head the third, offers a fair Accommodation, ſo as that there may be no Encounter betwixt the Myſtery and the Letter, or betwixt the grand Senſe and the very Words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> diſcours'd upon the Harmonical Context, from p. 38. to p. 44.</item>
                  <item>General Head the fourth, is taken up in an Enquiry, How there came ſuch a Notion into the Chriſtian Church, as that fleſhly Tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, ſo earneſtly contended for, and finds it ariſing from four Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<list>
                        <item>1. From the great myſtery of ſpiritual Tranſubſtantiation, given in that our ſo magnified <hi>Sixth of John,</hi> and in the Inſtitution of the Lord's Supper, <hi>p.</hi> 44.</item>
                        <item>2. From the Ancients and Fathers diſcourſing with high Eloquence of this Point, not ſufficiently guarded, <hi>p.</hi> 45.</item>
                        <item>3. From the Ignorance and Barbarity which after them invaded the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church, <hi>p.</hi> 46.</item>
                        <item>4. From the riſing of a Church-Power at the ſame time over mens Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and preſſing this as an Article of Faith, <hi>p.</hi> 47.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>General Head the fifth, ſhews the danger of ſuch a Doctrine as fleſhly Tranſubſtantiation.
<list>
                        <item>1. As it ſhakes the Credit of all our knowing and judging Faculties, <hi>p.</hi> 48, 49.</item>
                        <item>2. As it makes void the Divineneſs of Scripture-Language, expreſſing ſpiritual things by ſenſible, and indeed perverts the Wiſdom of all Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage ſo doing, <hi>p.</hi> 49.</item>
                        <item>3. As it amuſes Mens Minds, and draws them off from ſpiritual Action in Holy Myſteries, <hi>p.</hi> 49.</item>
                        <item>4. The great danger eſpecially lies in bringing down God into a contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, vile Appearance, and allowing divine Honour to it; which is one
<pb facs="tcp:57608:5"/> ſort of Idolatry Scripture moſt abhors, <hi>p.</hi> 50 to 52.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>General Head the ſixth draws all into ſix practical Applications, <hi>p.</hi> 52. <hi>to the end,</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. By propoſal to our choice the most worthy of theſe two, The spiritual, or the carnal Tranſubſtantiation.</item>
                        <item>2. By raiſing us to high Thoughts of the Redemption of Jeſus Christ, ſo uniting it ſelf to us, as by eating and drinking his Body and Blood.</item>
                        <item>3. By lifting up our Hearts to Chriſt eating the Paſſover, and drinking the very ſame Fruit of the Vine with us by his Interceſſion in Heaven, which he did here on Earth.</item>
                        <item>4. By obliging us to a high value of this Ordinance of the Lord's Supper, in which we ſo unite to Christ.</item>
                        <item>5. By perſwading us to an earnest care against violating ſo great a My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, as Christ eaten and drunk in the Goſpel, and the Lord's Supper.</item>
                        <item>6. By lifting up our Heads in Prayers and Deſires to the Table of Christ in his Kingdom.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57608:5"/>
            <head>A SERMON OF THE True, Spiritual <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> oppos'd to the Groſs, Carnal, Imaginary <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>MATTH. 26. 26.</bibl>
               <q>Compar'd with <hi>Mark</hi> 14. 22. <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 23. <hi>&amp;c. This is my Body.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Take all theſe Scriptures, as the common Subject, that by the Grace and Aſſiſtance of God, I intend to diſcourſe at this time, and eſpecially to Treat the Senſe of theſe Words, <hi>This is my Body:</hi> And <hi>This Cup is my Blood of the New Teſtament.</hi> And as I have earneſtly begg'd of God, that he would <hi>waken me morning by morning,</hi> that he would <hi>waken my Ear to hear as the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> concerning it; ſo that He would give me the <hi>Tongue</hi> of the <hi>Learned</hi> to ſpeak of it; and grant you alſo to <hi>hear with the Ear of the Learned;</hi> that ſo in this whole Duty the <hi>Preparations of the Heart,</hi> the <hi>Anſwer of the Tongue,</hi> and the <hi>Hearing of the Ear,</hi> may be <hi>from the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I ſhall endeavour ſo to treat of it, as if there were no other Point of Controverſie between us Proteſtants and the <hi>Roman Perſuaſion,</hi> but only the Senſe of theſe Words,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57608:6"/> 
               <hi>This is my Body:</hi> And I ſhall conſider that <hi>Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> as it is generally called, that is built upon it, as if there were no other Fault nor Errour in that Doctrine, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>Zeal</hi> for the <hi>Myſtery of the Lord's Supper,</hi> and the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Scripture in this <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> though it be not <hi>according to Knowledge:</hi> and therefore I will allow the utmoſt both to the Words, and the Senſe, that can be allowed, the very utmoſt that can be made of <hi>This is my Body, This Cup is my Blood of the New Teſtament.</hi> And I ſhall endeavour ſo to treat of it, that there may be nothing that may be offenſive, except the plain Evidence and Reaſon of Things, the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Truth, without any umbrage, any ſhadow of a <hi>Railing Accuſation.</hi> I will diſcourſe only upon the ſingle Account of Scripture, and the Reaſons drawn from it.</p>
            <p>And therefore I do allow, That theſe Words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> and <hi>This Cup is my Blood,</hi> they do carry a moſt high and important Senſe; And I ſhall conſider the utmoſt Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency they can have to ſuch a thing as is called <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation:</hi> though the Word it ſelf be not indeed found in Scripture, yet I will allow the thing in its due ſenſe. And I ſhall endeavour ſo to do this, that you may have the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt underſtanding of the Intention and Meaning of the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> and the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of it, and of theſe Words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> and ſo as may tend moſt to the real Senſe, and Impreſſion upon your Hearts, of ſo great an Expreſſion of our Saviour both in the general Doctrine of the Goſpel, and in the particular Senſe and Meaning of the <hi>Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> and that ſacred Solemnity; and alſo may be moſt pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical, and may moſt ſerve to the good of every man's Soul who deſires ſpiritually to underſtand this great Doctrine, and the particular Ordinance of the <hi>Lord's Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe it is agreed among all men that profeſs any Reverence to the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> that as it is not a humane Device, ſo not a natural Duty, made known by natural Light, nor written in natural Conſcience; it is not like the Reverence of the Divine Being, or Prayer to God, or the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57608:6"/> deſire to know his Mind or Will, or any moral Duty: but it depends wholly upon Divine Inſtitution and Ordination: 'Tis wholly from Scripture, or elſe there could never have been ſuch a Worſhip of God known in the World, as the Solemnity of <hi>eating Bread,</hi> and <hi>drinking Wine</hi> in the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> in <hi>Remembrance of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To introduce therefore this matter, I conſider, There are Four inſpired Writers who have given us this Inſtitution from our Lord; the <hi>Evangelist Matthew,</hi> the <hi>Evangelist Mark,</hi> the <hi>Evangelist Luke,</hi> and the <hi>Apostle Paul:</hi> and then the <hi>Evangelist John,</hi> although it was not committed to him (as every <hi>Evangelist</hi> had throughout the whole <hi>Evangelick</hi> Hiſtory, his Portion of every Matter, and the proper Words of it committed to him) to write of this <hi>Inſtitution;</hi> yet he had a ſublime and highly ſpiritual Diſcourſe intruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him all along the laſt part of his ſixth Chapter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>eating the Fleſh of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>drinking his Blood;</hi> which muſt needs be the Foundation of <hi>eating the Fleſh of Christ, and drinking his Blood</hi> in the <hi>Sacrament:</hi> for a <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</hi> muſt have a Doctrine to ſuſtain it, that it may not be an inſignificant Ceremony: and what can have nearer Relation to the Sacrament of <hi>eating the Body of Chriſt bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for us,</hi> and <hi>drinking his Blood of the New Teſtament ſhed for many, than eating his Fleſh, and drinking his Blood, which he gave for the life of the World,</hi> which is <hi>Meat indeed</hi> and <hi>Drink indeed,</hi> which the <hi>Evangeliſt John</hi> relates from Chriſt, of which <hi>whoever eats ſhall live by him for ever,</hi> and <hi>he will raiſe him up at the last day,</hi> viz. at his <hi>Coming,</hi> till which <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming there is a ſhewing forth of his Death</hi> in this <hi>Supper,</hi> viz. a declaring that efficacy of it which ſhall then appear. And it is certain, though Chriſt had not yet inſtituted this ſacred Rite, nor did till ſome conſiderable ſpace after this great Diſcourſe, yet he knew his own Intention concerning it, and he knew, this Doctrine ſhould be in its juſt Time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by himſelf, to be repreſented in that Rite; and his Death, as a <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> he continually enlivens, and keeps,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57608:7"/> new, vigorous, and in full force by his <hi>Interceſſion</hi> upon it, in which Interceſſion he appears with his own Blood in the true <hi>Holy of Holies,</hi> as the <hi>High priest</hi> with the <hi>Blood</hi> of the Typical Sacrifices in that Typical <hi>Holieſt.</hi> All which becomes a moſt eſpecial Preparation of his Fleſh to be <hi>eaten</hi> and <hi>drunk</hi> in the Lord's Supper: therefore the Lord's Supper is ſo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar an <hi>Annunciation of his Death till he comes; viz.</hi> in the <hi>eating his Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>drinking his Blood,</hi> now become a <hi>Peace-offering</hi> by his <hi>Interceſſion,</hi> and to be <hi>feaſted</hi> upon.</p>
            <p>Now in theſe four ſacred Pen-men of this <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> 'tis obſervable, That they are all uniform in theſe Words, <hi>This is my Body:</hi> there's not any difference among them, from one to the other, not any variety found: they all with one Mouth ſay to a very Tittle, <hi>This is my Body.</hi> But they are not ſo uniform concerning the <hi>Cup:</hi> The <hi>Evangelist Matthew</hi> and the <hi>Evangelist Mark,</hi> ſay, <hi>This Cup is my Blood of the New Teſtament:</hi> The <hi>Evangeliſt Luke,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtle Paul,</hi> ſay, <hi>This Cup is the New Teſtament in my Blood:</hi> ſo here's thus much of variety, Two ſay, <hi>This is my Blood of the New Teſtament;</hi> two others ſay, <hi>This is the New Teſtament in my Blood.</hi> And this I do account will give us great light into the ſenſe of this <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> as you ſhall perceive in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of this Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>That which is yet farther conſiderable, is, that the <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> ſays, <hi>That which I received of the Lord I deliver'd unto</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 23.</note> 
               <hi>you:</hi> by which Words, there is great Reaſon to believe, that the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> as a <hi>fourth Evangelist,</hi> receiv'd this <hi>Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> immediately from the <hi>Revelation of Jeſus Christ,</hi> and that it is part of that <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which he tells us, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 11, 12. <hi>he received not from men, neither was taught it, but by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> ſo that I think we may certainly and ſafely conclude, He was not only inſpired as a ſacred Writer of that <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Corinths,</hi> but Chriſt had before that, at the time of his Call to the <hi>Apoſtleſhip,</hi> made an immediate <hi>Revelation</hi> of this <hi>Inſtitution</hi> to him; which, as it ſhews the great excellency of this <hi>holy Sacrament,</hi> ſo to this Apoſtle
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57608:7"/> was committed, as his peculiar part, to ſhew the Obligato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs of this Ordinance upon all Ages till <hi>Chriſt's coming,</hi> which is not given in expreſs terms, but by him only.</p>
            <p>All this being premis'd, it is of concern in the next place, to give you an exact <hi>Harmony</hi> of theſe <hi>four ſacred Writers,</hi> and what they have written concerning this <hi>Inſtitution:</hi> that is, out of all the words of each of them drawn out, and laid together, to make up one even Text of the whole, which, by Interpreters, is call'd a <hi>Harmony.</hi> And thus it is, as I ſhall draw it out of the <hi>Apoſtle Paul,</hi> as infolding the whole <hi>Inſtitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>I received of the Lord that which I deliver'd unto you, that the Lord Jeſus the Night in which he was betray'd, while they were eating that Paſſover, of which he had <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 23.</note> ſaid, <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 15, 16. [With Deſire have I deſired to eat this Paſſover with you before I ſuffer, For I ſay unto you, I will not any more eat thereof until it be fulfilled in the <note place="margin">Luc. 22. 19.</note> Kingdom of God,] he took the Bread, which we break, and bleſſed it with Thankſgiving, and gave it to his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and ſaid, Take, eat, this is my Body, <hi>viz.</hi> the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 16. which is broken for you, This do in Remembrance of me. In the ſame manner, after Supper, when he had ſupped, He took the Cup of Bleſſing, which we bleſs, and when he had given Thanks, he gave it to them, ſaying to them, Divide it among your ſelves, and drink you all of it; For this Cup is my Blood of the New <note place="margin">Matt. 26. 28. Marc. 14. 24.</note> Teſtament, and this Cup is the New Teſtament in my Blood, <hi>viz.</hi> in the Communion of it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 16. which is ſhed for you and for many for the Remiſſion of ſins. [And they drank all of it,] <hi>Mark</hi> 14. 23. This do as often as ye drink it in Remembrance of me. As often therefore as ye eat this Bread, and drink this Cup, ye ſhew forth the Lord's Death till he come, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 26.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This is that, which laid together ariſes out of all theſe <hi>four Evangeliſts</hi> (accounting the <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> for one,) and comprizing this <hi>Inſtitution</hi> in what immediately concerns
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57608:8"/> the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> it ſelf, wholly and fully. And before it we may place the ſixth Chapter of the <hi>Evangelist John,</hi> begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at <hi>v.</hi> 27. as giving the Doctrine that ſupports this <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution.</hi> And out of this <hi>Harmony</hi> I ſhall endeavour to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe at this time.</p>
            <p>Now it is certain, this <hi>harmonical</hi> Context muſt be true in every <hi>Iota</hi> of it; and whatever is fuller in any part, muſt inlighten and clear the whole; and whatever is obſcure in any part, or curt, and ſhort, muſt be enlarged from what is more clear and full. For you know one Writer is as true as another in whatever we place, as from them to this matter. The very Order in which they give this <hi>Inſtitution</hi> is much to be conſidered; and if in any particular there ſeems any thing that does encounter, and run croſs, one thing with another, it muſt be ſo explain'd, as that the whole, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part, may be moſt conciliated with it ſelf; ſo that the whole muſt be both clear'd, and illuſtrated, and reconcil'd by the concert of every part, and every part by it ſelf in compare with the other parts: of all which we are to make our Advantages; as,</p>
            <p n="1">1. When we find the whole Concert of the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> ſo <hi>one</hi> in theſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> we know, That in them is moſt plainly, poſitively, forcibly, deliver'd the real Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation and Communion of the Body of Jeſus in the Lord's Supper; as we ſhall find all the words joyn'd with them, viz. <hi>Bleſſing, Breaking, Taking, Eating a Body broken for us,</hi> lead us unto and make this <hi>Bread</hi> the <hi>Communion of Chriſt's Body;</hi> as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> calls it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When we find the four Records of this <hi>Inſtitution</hi> agree in the <hi>Cup,</hi> even as in the <hi>Body,</hi> thus far, that the <hi>drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of it is an equal part of the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> with <hi>the eating the Body:</hi> that it appears in every one, it had its diſtinct <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Bleſſing,</hi> even as the <hi>Bread:</hi> that it hath ſome peculiar marks, as the particular Command, <hi>Divide it among your ſelves, Drink all of it;</hi> do this very particular thing, <hi>as oft as ye drink it in remembrance of me:</hi> that the matter of Fact
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57608:8"/> concerning it is peculiarly recited, viz. <hi>They All drank of it:</hi> that the <hi>Apoſtle calls it the Cup of Bleſſing.</hi> All this ſpeaks two things; That the <hi>Cup</hi> is as eſſential a part of the <hi>Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi> as the <hi>Bread,</hi> of as high Neceſſity and Dignity; and the Precept of one as extenſive as the other, and of the Two the moſt particularly remark'd in its Extenſiveneſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That it is worthy to explain the ſenſe of thoſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> and the meaning of the <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> upon what occaſion or account ſoever it ſhall be ſo urg'd; ſeeing as the Doctrine of the <hi>Blood ſhed of Christ</hi> hath the Equality and rather the Preference to the Body (if there could be any odds) throughout the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> as being the laſt and completory Act of Chriſt's <hi>ſacrificing</hi> himſelf, and is therefore ſo expreſly nam'd in that <hi>Tri-unity</hi> of Teſtimonies on <hi>Earth,</hi> The <hi>Spirit,</hi> the <hi>Water,</hi> the BLOOD, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. 8.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When therefore we find two ſacred Pen-men of this <hi>Inſtitution</hi> write, <hi>This Cup is my Blood of the New Teſtament,</hi> and two other, of which one by <hi>immediate Revelation, This Cup is the New Teſtament in my Blood,</hi> we thus collect; It cannot be indeed ſo probable Chriſt ſaid both (if he did, what I urge will be the ſtronger:) but I allow he ſaid only one, and that it was, <hi>This is my Blood,</hi> yet is this explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Alteration moſt Authentick and Divine: ſo that there ſhall be as full a ſenſe of the Blood offered to us in the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</hi> as of the <hi>Body,</hi> by thoſe Words, <hi>This Cup is my Blood, &amp;c.</hi> and yet the Explication of them ſhall limit that Preſence to ſuch a one as will bear thoſe Words, <hi>It is the New Teſtament in my Blood,</hi> (omitting the Figure of this <hi>Cup</hi> for the Wine in the <hi>Cup,</hi> which yet ſhews, Chriſt did not abhor from Figure in this <hi>Inſtitution;)</hi> and ſo ſhews a <hi>myſtical</hi> ſenſe: and ſeeing the <hi>Wine</hi> in the <hi>Lord's Supper</hi> is equal to the <hi>Bread,</hi> even as the <hi>Blood</hi> in the Doctrine of the <hi>New Teſtament to the Body of Christ,</hi> it ſhall have power to limit the ſenſe of thoſe Words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> to ſuch a <hi>Myſticalneſs,</hi> as agrees to the Wine, being the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Christ's Blood.</hi> And when the Apoſtle explains both,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57608:9"/> by the <hi>Communion</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> and of the <hi>Blood of Christ;</hi> it limits the ſenſe ſo, that the <hi>Bread</hi> is not the <hi>Body,</hi> nor the <hi>Cup</hi> the <hi>Blood,</hi> in any other ſenſe than the Communion of each is ſo, as ſhall be farther argued: For theſe Words explain, by divine Authority, <hi>This is my Body, this is my Blood,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch a ſenſe, that it may be true, This Bread is the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Body of Chriſt, this Cup the Communion of his Blood.</p>
            <p n="5">5. When the <hi>Evangeliſts, Matthew, Mark, Luke,</hi> all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord the Saying of Chriſt, <hi>I will no more drink of the Fruit of the Vine,</hi> the Evangeliſt <hi>Matthew</hi> emphatically of <hi>[this] Fruit;</hi> and the Evangeliſt <hi>Luke</hi> prefixes of the <hi>Paſſover,</hi> and anti-dates part of the Inſtitution of the <hi>Cup,</hi> that he might joyn the like important Saying of our Saviour, concerning <hi>the Fruit of the Vine, That he will not eat any more of the Paſſover,</hi> nor <hi>drink of the Fruit of the Vine, till the Paſſover</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Which by the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> muſt be <hi>This Fruit.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>be fulfilled in the Kingdom of God,</hi> and till he <hi>drink of the Fruit of the Vine a new in the Kingdom of God his Father,</hi> when it ſhall come: and the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>We ſhew forth the Lord's Death till he come:</hi> From hence it may be argued, That there was another manner of Preſence of Chriſt to be expected than was juſt then, at the <hi>eating and drinking</hi> with his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> and that ſuch a one was to be expected in the <hi>Kingdom of God, his Father:</hi> ſo that he would no more <hi>eat</hi> nor <hi>drink</hi> with them, either in the ſame manner of <hi>bodily Preſence,</hi> nor in the way of Anticipation, or of <hi>eating that Paſſover, and that Fruit of the Vine,</hi> which at the time of this firſt Inſtitution was not yet ſacrificed, nor the Blood yet offer'd; but in ſuch a manner as would agree to the <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of all,</hi> the <hi>renewing of all in the Kingdom of God, and his Father,</hi> when that ſhould <hi>come,</hi> after that <hi>Paſſover</hi> ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic'd, and that Blood offer'd; of which we ſhall after en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire: for this I eſteem of great moment in this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, When we find the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 17. making that Queſtion <hi>[The Bread which we break, is it not the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:57608:9"/> 
               <hi>of the Body of Christ?</hi> and ſubjoyning in the very ſame Contexture, in the ſame Ayr, and manner of Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>[We being many are one Bread, and one Body,</hi> for we <hi>are all partakers of that one Bread,]</hi> muſt we not needs infer, the ſenſe in both <hi>[This is my Body]</hi> and <hi>[We are all one Bread and one Body]</hi> muſt be alike one myſtical Senſe? for ſeeing common ſenſe teaches us, All Chriſtians cannot be <hi>one Bread</hi> and <hi>one Body,</hi> but in a myſtical ſenſe; no more can the <hi>Bread</hi> be <hi>Chriſt's Body,</hi> but in ſuch a myſtical ſenſe: and the very Letter can no more oblige us in the one than in the other.</p>
            <p>All which is much enforc'd by the Conſideration, The No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>eating the Fleſh of Christ,</hi> and of <hi>drinking his Blood,</hi> were given before the <hi>Lord's Supper</hi> inſtituted: and though I doubt not Chriſt deſign'd it as a Foundation of that <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> as I ſaid before, yet it had been a true Doctrine, if that <hi>Supper</hi> had not been inſtituted, as a Repreſentation of it; becauſe Chriſt, as a <hi>Sacrifice, gave himſelf for the Life of the World,</hi> and <hi>offer'd</hi> himſelf to the Faith and Participation of his believing Servants, as it were to be <hi>Eaten</hi> and <hi>Drunk</hi> by them, had not the <hi>Lord's Supper</hi> been appointed.</p>
            <p>Thus far I have endeavoured to prepare the way for this Diſcourſe, by laying a Foundation upon this <hi>Harmonical</hi> Context for it: and indeed I deſire in proſecuting it to uſe little more than Scripture Notions and Words: and if I can be ſo happy, by the Aſſiſtance of God, to expreſs the things as plain to you as I apprehend it in my own Mind, I doubt not to give you a ſatisfactory Account of theſe Words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> and alſo of the ſenſe of this great Ordinance of the <hi>Lord's Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In doing this, I propoſe this Method:</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall endeavour to give a clear Reſolution, How Chriſt may be ſaid to <hi>give us his Fleſh to eat,</hi> and <hi>his Blood to drink:</hi> for that was the great Stumble that thoſe who heard Chriſt upon this Point, <hi>John</hi> 6. made.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:57608:10"/> 2. I ſhall from thence endeavour to ſhew you, That there is a clear Paſſage and Tranſition from that <hi>giving his Fleſh to eat,</hi> and <hi>his Blood to drink,</hi> into thoſe Words, <hi>Take, eat, this is my Body,</hi> or from the <hi>Doctrine</hi> into the <hi>Sacrament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. I ſhall endeavour to find a fair Accommodation, and no Encounter betwixt the <hi>Myſtery</hi> and the <hi>Letter,</hi> or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the grand ſenſe and the very Words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> by a compare of this whole Harmonical Context with other Scripture, and its way of ſpeaking in ſuch Caſes.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I will enquire into this Thing, How there came ſuch a Notion into the Chriſtian Church as that <hi>fleſhly Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation,</hi> ſo earneſtly contended for.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I will repreſent to you the danger of ſuch a Doctrine as that <hi>Fleſhly Tranſubſtantiation;</hi> not ſo much as it is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templative thing, a Notion, a manner of Apprehenſion, or matter of Diſcourſe; but as it carries the Practice of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Adoration.</p>
            <p n="6">6. I will cloſe all with practical Applications, tending to a conſtant habitual Preparation for the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Lord's Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to diſcharge the firſt part of this Undertaking, I muſt eſtabliſh theſe following Points:</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Divine Perſon</hi> of our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> taking <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Point </seg>1</label> the <hi>Humane Nature</hi> upon him, that <hi>Humane Nature</hi> is moſt emphatically expreſs'd in theſe Words, <hi>his Body,</hi> and <hi>his Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>his Blood:</hi> or, the <hi>Body,</hi> and <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Chriſt are the moſt fit Expreſſions that could be choſen to ſet out the <hi>Humane Nature</hi> of Chriſt, or to ſet out <hi>the Man Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Now this being rightly apprehended, ſhews, There is the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and there is <hi>the Blood of Chriſt,</hi> that are to be <hi>eaten</hi> and <hi>drunk</hi> by Believers in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Body,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Blood of Chriſt,</hi> and the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Point </seg>2</label> Actions of Chriſt in his <hi>Body,</hi> in his <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> were as ſo many Preparations of his <hi>Body, Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> to be ſpiritually <hi>eaten</hi> by, or applied to the Souls of Believers, or communicated by them.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:57608:10"/>
            <p> That the <hi>Body,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Blood</hi> of Chriſt, are ſo <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Point </seg>3</label> many Reſts and Repoſitories of the <hi>Divine Power, Spirit,</hi> and <hi>Efficacy,</hi> filling them with infinite ſaving Vertue and Effect in their Communication to the Souls of Believers in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>divine Power, Spirit,</hi> and <hi>Efficacy,</hi> extends the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Point </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>Body, Fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Blood</hi> of Chriſt in their ſaving Vertue and Effect, without limitation to Time or Place; and to all Dimenſions and degrees of Effect.</p>
            <p>The firſt Point, <hi>viz.</hi> That the moſt expreſſive and ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Point </seg>1</label> Terms concerning the <hi>Man Christ Jeſus,</hi> that the Spirit of God hath choſen, throughout the Scripture, are the <hi>Fleſh of Christ,</hi> the <hi>Body of Christ,</hi> and the <hi>Blood of Christ.</hi> This is the firſt Branch of the <hi>Myſtery of Godlineſs; God manifeſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 16. 1 John 4. 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>in the fleſh, Jeſus Christ come in the fleſh,</hi> is made the grand Principle of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>The whole <hi>Humane Nature of Christ,</hi> in which the <hi>Son of God was manifeſt,</hi> is called <hi>Fleſh: The Word was made Fleſh,</hi> John 1. 14. So the <hi>Body of Chriſt,</hi> how often is it mention'd? <hi>The offering of the Body of Chriſt once for all.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 10. 1 Pet. 2. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Who bare our Sins in his Body on the tree.</hi> And in all the New Teſtament, there is nothing ſo memorializ'd as the <hi>Blood of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Reaſon is this; Becauſe theſe, The <hi>Body,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Blood,</hi> are the moſt viſible Repreſentations of <hi>Humane Nature;</hi> and ſo in Scripture, and all Language, they are the readieſt, eaſieſt, and moſt familiar Expreſſions of Humane Nature. The Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> therefore ſo often in his Epiſtle expreſſes the whole Doctrine of the <hi>Meſſiah, by Chriſt come in the fleſh;</hi> that is, <hi>God manifeſted in fleſh.</hi> So that, though it is true, Man is chiefly Soul and Spirit, and ſo to be conſidered, yet he is moſt viſible, moſt apparent, in Body, Fleſh, and Blood; and Humane Nature is ſo fram'd and conſtituted, that it deſires moſt to appear and diſplay it ſelf in a Body.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:57608:11"/>
            <p> And though God and Chriſt have a peculiar Care and Account of the <hi>Spirits of juſt men,</hi> yet they are not <hi>Perfect</hi> without <hi>Bodies;</hi> and till Chriſt does appear again in <hi>a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Glory,</hi> He is not <hi>ſhewn.</hi> Pray conſider, Though He's now in a <hi>Body of Glory,</hi> yet till he appears in this <hi>Body,</hi> that <hi>every Eye may ſee him,</hi> God does not till that time <hi>ſhew him,</hi> whom he will <hi>ſhew,</hi> who is the <hi>onely Potentate, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 15.</note> that is, He will ſhew Chriſt Jeſus, in a <hi>Body of Glory,</hi> at his <hi>Appearance,</hi> though Chriſt hath been in a <hi>Body of Glory</hi> ever ſince his <hi>Aſcenſion.</hi> So <hi>Juſt Men</hi> are not made Perfect, <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 23.</note> till they appear in a <hi>Body at the Reſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although therefore the Soul of Jeſus Chriſt (underſtand I beſeech you, what I ſay) was the Principal Agent in all the Work of Redemption, yet it was, as in a Body, in the Action and Paſſion of a Body.</p>
            <p>It was not indeed a Body that acted, that ſuffered, that dyed, yet it was in a Body. It was the Humane Soul and Spirit of Chriſt that came to do <hi>the Will of God,</hi> and <hi>a Body was prepared him, Hebr.</hi> 10. 5. It was not a Body, but a Soul, a Will in Chriſt that ſurrender'd it ſelf to the <hi>Will of God,</hi> that ſaid, <hi>Not my Will, but thine be done.</hi> It was a Spirit that ſurrender'd it ſelf to God, <hi>Into thy hands I commit my Spirit:</hi> yet it was in a Body. So it was in the <hi>Circumciſion</hi> of Chriſt; it was the <hi>Circumciſion</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> not of the <hi>Letter.</hi> Soul and Spirit was the Life and Excellency of all: yet all this was viſible in a Body, it was viſible in Fleſh and Blood. So it was in Chriſt's <hi>fulfilling All Righteouſneſs in his Baptiſm,</hi> in all the Holineſs of Life; There was an Humane Soul, a Spirit, that acted in and throughout All, yet All was ſtill viſible in a Body. His Soul ſent out <hi>Strong Cries</hi> and <hi>Fears,</hi> with that he <hi>offer'd Prayers</hi> and <hi>Supplications,</hi> but it was <hi>in the days of his Fleſh, Hebr.</hi> 5. 7. He was <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, Baptized, Died in a Body.</hi> He aroſe again in a Body, and in ſuch a Body as we carry about with us: but juſt at his <hi>Aſcenſion,</hi> then undoubtedly, in the very Time of his <hi>Aſcending up to Heaven,</hi> his Body was changed into a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57608:11"/> 
               <hi>Glorious Body:</hi> ſo that That Body which was in a ſtate of <hi>Humiliation,</hi> which he carried with him in the World, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his <hi>Aſcenſion</hi> remained no longer in thoſe Circumſtances of humbled <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> he underwent while he was here in the World; for, <hi>Fleſh and Blood cannot inherit the Kingdom of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 50. and therefore the dayes of Chriſt's Humiliation are call'd the <hi>Days of his Fleſh.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore obſerve, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi> The <hi>myſtery of Godlineſs</hi> is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd in that, <hi>Receiv'd, Taken up into Glory:</hi> and there he is hidden to us, though ſwallowed up in the Perfection and Excellency of Glory till God <hi>ſhews him,</hi> till he <hi>appears,</hi> and is <hi>revealed in that Glory:</hi> From all which amounts, That the whole undertaking of Chriſt was in <hi>Body,</hi> and his Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is now in <hi>Body,</hi> though a <hi>Body of Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now from hence you may perceive what I drive at; <hi>viz.</hi> That there was great Reaſon that Chriſt ſhould ſay, <hi>This is my Body, This is my Blood;</hi> becauſe the <hi>Body of Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh and Blood of Chriſt,</hi> was that which was viſibly and ſenſibly active, and was to be ſo throughout the whole Work of our Redemption; for, <hi>Foraſmuch as the Children</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 14: 17.</note> 
               <hi>were Partakers of Fleſh and Blood, he himſelf took part of the ſame,</hi> that <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And <hi>it behooved him in all things to be made like unto his Brethren.</hi> The holy Humane Soul, and Spirit of Chriſt, was the principal Agent; the <hi>Body, Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Chriſt, was the Theatre upon which All was made publick, the Tube and Channel through which All is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey'd: therefore the whole <hi>Humane Nature</hi> is expreſs'd by <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> the Repreſentation of it and the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of it is ſo given in the Doctrine, and therefore ſo in the <hi>Lord's Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Body, Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Chriſt, and all his Action <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Point </seg>2</label> and Suffering in it, were as ſo many Preparations, that he may be ſpiritually <hi>eaten,</hi> applied to, and communicated with, by the Souls of Believers; of which his Death is the moſt comprehenſive, and principal, as that, in which center not only his <hi>Incarnation, Circumciſion, Baptiſm,</hi> Holy Life, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57608:12"/> in the <hi>Days of his Fleſh,</hi> but even his <hi>Reſurrection, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion, Interceſſion at the Right-hand of God:</hi> and therefore as the Doctrine of the <hi>Communion of his Body</hi> ſtyles his <note place="margin">John 6. 51.</note> Death, the <hi>giving his Fleſh for the Life of the World,</hi> ſo the Sacrament of it in the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> calls it his <hi>Body given for us,</hi> and the <hi>Remembrance of his Death:</hi> and the whole Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication by Faith is call'd <hi>Eating</hi> in both.</p>
            <p>And proportionably in ſenſe, Chriſt was ſent <hi>in the Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 3.</note> 
               <hi>of ſinful Fleſh,</hi> that he might <hi>condemn Sin in the Fleſh, that the Righteouſneſs of the Law might be fulfilled in us: We put off the Sins of the Fleſh</hi> by the <hi>Circumciſion of Chriſt;</hi> we <note place="margin">Col. 2. 11.</note> 
               <hi>are buried in his Baptiſm,</hi> we riſe in <hi>his Reſurrection,</hi> and <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 4.</note> know the Power of it, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 10. We ſit in Heavenly Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in him. He makes <hi>Interceſſion for us,</hi> and ſo ſaves to the uttermoſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 25. And his <hi>Death</hi> is in all Senſes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to us. All which are in other Words the very ſame thing with <hi>giving us his Fleſh te eat,</hi> and his <hi>Blood to drink.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>humane Nature</hi> of Chriſt, call'd his <hi>Body,</hi> his <hi>Fleſh,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Point. </seg>3</label> and his <hi>Blood,</hi> and all his Actions and Sufferings in it, were ſo many Reſts and Repoſitories of the Divine Nature, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Efficacy, and Virtue of Jeſus Chriſt; filling them with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite ſaving Virtue and Effect in their Communication to the Senſes of Believers in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For in all the Action, and Sufferings of Chriſt, the Son of God was immediately Active, the Divine Power and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit was always preſent, and Active in all, as a ſupreme Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Soul.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Incarnation</hi> of Chriſt was a ſenſible, fleſhly, and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily Thing; But there was a Manifeſtation of <hi>Divinity</hi> in it. The <hi>Power of the moſt High over-ſhadowed</hi> the <hi>Virgin,</hi> and <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 2.</note> Chriſt was <hi>Conceiv'd,</hi> as we daily Profeſs, by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt: The Law of the Spirit of Life,</hi> purified the <hi>Humane Nature</hi> of Chriſt to the higheſt Elevation of Purity: The <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion</hi> of Chriſt was a <hi>Divine Circumciſion made without</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Col. 2. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Hands,</hi> by the immediate Action of the Divine Spirit; for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57608:12"/> if ours were ſo, much more His, the original of it. The <hi>Baptiſm</hi> of Chriſt was full of a Divine Preſence; The <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit reſted like a Dove upon Him; This is my beloved Son,</hi> &amp;c. <note place="margin">Matt. 3. 18. Philip. 3. 9.</note> His Obedience and Righteouſneſs was the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God.</hi> In his Death he offer'd Himſelf by the <hi>Eternal Spirit,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9. 14.</note> His Blood is called the <hi>Blood of God.</hi> He Roſe <hi>by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 20. 28.</note> 
               <hi>of Holineſs,</hi> which <hi>Juſtified</hi> Him. He is <hi>made higher than the Heavens</hi> in his <hi>Interceſſion.</hi> And this is of ſupreme Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration in all the Communications of Chriſt, in all our <hi>Eating</hi> and <hi>Drinking his Fleſh</hi> and <hi>his Blood,</hi> as may be ſeen in that excellent Diſcourſe, <hi>John</hi> 6. to which the <hi>Lord's Supper</hi> is a parallel Repreſentation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As the Living Father hath ſent me, and I live by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">v. 57.</note> 
               <hi>even ſo he that eateth me ſhall live by me.</hi> For his <hi>Fleſh</hi> eaten is the Conduit of divine Life. <hi>It is the Spirit,</hi> viz. the Divine Nature, <hi>that quickneth. The Fleſh, profiteth nothing.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">v. 63.</note> 
               <hi>The Words that I ſpeak unto you, are Spirit,</hi> and <hi>they are Life;</hi> that is, by the Vertue and Preſence of the Divinity, of which they were ſpoken; for by <hi>Power he is declar'd to be</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 4.</note> the <hi>Son of God; viz.</hi> by the Power of the Divinity. <hi>He was</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13. 4.</note> 
               <hi>put to death through weakneſs, but he liveth by the Power of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 18.</note> 
               <hi>God. He was put to death in the Fleſh, quickned by the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any Man therefore conſiders the Actions of Jeſus Chriſt in the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and does not conſider the <hi>Divine Nature</hi> in them, he does not conſider that which our Saviour ſays, <hi>Quickens.</hi> He only conſiders that which our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Profits nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From hence therefore, it is plainly firſt to be underſtood, that it is moſt impoſſible, Material or Bodily ſhould by it ſelf do any thing, to that which is Spiritual, Immaterial, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual, as is the Soul of Man. The Sun, though ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious a Body, can do nothing to Man's Soul immediately; and ſuppoſe the Body of Chriſt as much higher in Glory than any thing we know in Nature, as the Sun excells a Turf of Earth; yet this very glorious Body can do nothing to our
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57608:13"/> Souls, to our Spirits: It can do nothing in theſe great Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiations of Peace with God, Purification of our Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Sanctification.</p>
            <p>This is ſo acknowledg'd a thing, that you know, as many as know any thing of Tranſubſtantiation, as it is held in the <hi>Roman Perſuaſion,</hi> That they themſelves confeſs, That if a Man Eat that very <hi>tranſubſtantiated Body,</hi> and Drink that very <hi>tranſubſtantiated Blood</hi> of Chriſt, though it is, as they ſuppoſe, the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Chriſt in the moſt fleſhly ſenſible Preſence we can imagine; yet it does a wicked Man no good, a Man who hath not Faith and Repentance: And it is very true, it muſt needs be ſo, becauſe it is a material thing, and cannot act ſo as to act up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſpiritual and immaterial Things; on the other ſide, it can do no hurt to theſe immaterial Beings. But if it did operate after the manner of material Things upon material, I cannot conceive how it ſhould miſs the beſt Effect, ſeeing it is infinitely prepar'd to do good in that very Caſe of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſed Evil of Sin: but when it is ſpiritual, and requires ſpiritual Preparation to receive it, or elſe it is not receiv'd, it then does not work Good where that Preparation is not, becauſe it is not receiv'd; but if it be receiv'd, it hath its certain Effect. On the other ſide, when it is not receiv'd it does hurt by way of increaſing Guilt; becauſe a ſpiritual Offer, of ſo excellent a Nature, is refus'd and contemn'd, and becauſe the Soul, by ſuch pretence of receiving, and yet Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſal, grows much more confirm'd in Evil.</p>
            <p>But this is not all; for though the Holineſs and Spiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of a Holy, Created, Finite Spirit, may by Inſtruction, Suggeſtion, or Example, offer much Good to other Spirits, and be inſtrumental in affecting them aright; yet, this is in all Regards in ſo finite and limited a way, that the Effect may be very ſmall, or none at all: and ſo it is not poſſible in any more than a very low and abated ſenſe, to eat or to drink of the Communications of any Angel or Saint above or below. But now whatever is divine is communicative,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57608:13"/> even to what degrees it pleaſes. All Finite is Poor and Scanty, and hath not for it ſelf, but as received. But the Son of God in Humane Nature hath all <hi>Fulneſs dwelling in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Col. 1. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Him;</hi> and ſo can derive and convey to what degrees he thinks fit. Of which is to be ſpoken in the next Particular. But this Aſſures in Chriſt there is Meat and Drink abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Life of the World.</p>
            <p>The Divine Power of the <hi>Son of God,</hi> and its Efficacy <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Point </seg>4</label> extend the Body, Fleſh, and Blood of Chriſt, and his Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on therein in their ſaving Virtue, and Effect without limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to Time or Place, and to all dimenſions and degrees of Effect.</p>
            <p>And under this Head I will undertake theſe three Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To ſhew that the <hi>Divine Nature of the Son of God,</hi> act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the <hi>Humane Nature</hi> united to Him, can draw out ſuch ſpiritual Powers and Efficacies from thoſe his Actings and Sufferings, as ſhall be moſt conducing to the Salvation of Souls that believe in Him; now this I ſhall make good by ſhewing what kind of Cauſalities, and what anſwerable Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects are by the Word of God aſcribed to the <hi>Divine Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> of Chriſt Acting in the <hi>Humane Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I will ſhew, that they cannot be prejudg'd nor hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by any diſtances of Time, becauſe of the <hi>Eternity</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt the <hi>Son of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That they cannot be intercepted by any diſtances of Place, becauſe of the <hi>Omnipreſence</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt <hi>the Son of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I ſhall not preſume to ſpeak of theſe Particulars, but as I am guided by the Spirit of God in his Word; For, Who can deſcribe the way of the Divine Spirit in Nature? Such Knowledge is too wonderful for me, I cannot attain to it; if not in Nature, how much more not in Grace and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturals? But yet it is not unworthy to be taken notice of, That all Philoſophy owns ſome kind of <hi>Effluviums,</hi> ſome flowing Atomes, <hi>Ramenta,</hi> or little Globules of matter,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57608:14"/> that fly every way, or if but ſome <hi>Sympathies</hi> in Nature, that paſs up and down, and fly unknown ways, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſurable diſtances, without the Load, Cumber, Preſence of thoſe Bodies from which they flow, which cannot move nor paſs as they do; if Spirits of much greater Efficacy are extracted, more agile, more portable, and more eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed than the Bodies themſelves from which they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted; if there are ſome Relations of unknown Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications of Minds at great diſtance of Bodies; Theſe may be taken notice of, as ſome Illuſtration of this matter: But ſuch things are too ſlippery and incertain, and alſo too groſs to reſt ſo great a Point upon, ſeeing what ſo infinite an Agent as the Spirit of Holineſs, can do, cannot be graſp'd or comprehended by any material Likeneſſes; its Extracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, its Abſtractions, are more ſubtile than our groſs Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions can find out or receive, or natural Agents imitate.</p>
            <p>There are yet in common Obſervation, ſome Inſtances, that may come nearer this great Point: From the vertuous Actions of great Perſonages in Bodies, there is an Honour, an Eſteem, a Dignity, an excellent Example flowing out, that continues Ages beyond the very Actions, and beyond the Perſons continuance in Bodies that perform'd them, and may be imputed to their Poſterity; and are, as it were, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracts from Perſons in Bodies, and yet of a ſpiritual kind of Diffuſiveneſs, as to both Time and Place, and much exceed the Places whereupon they were acted; that have a kind of Univerſality both as to Time and Place, are nearer the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we are upon, and yet they are but dark, and dull ſhades of ſo great a Truth: Let us therefore come to the Holy Word of God it ſelf, and we ſhall find four kinds of Cauſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity attributed to <hi>God manifeſted in Fleſh,</hi> and to all his Divine Action and ſuffering therein.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Cauſality of an expiatory, propitiatory, or meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Cauſe.</item>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:57608:14"/>
               <item> 2. Of an exemplar Cauſe.</item>
               <item>3. Of an efficient Cauſe, by way of Union to himſelf.</item>
               <item>4. Of a rational argumentative Cauſe, ſo effecting a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity of the Souls of his People to himſelf.</item>
            </list>
            <p>There is nothing more evident, than that the Goſpel aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribes <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cauſality </seg>1</label> to the <hi>Body, Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Chriſt, the Efficacy of an eternal, propitiatory, expiatory Cauſe: <hi>By one Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 14.</note> 
               <hi>of the Body of Christ,</hi> and that <hi>once for all, He hath for ever perfected,</hi> that is, reconcil'd and conſecrated, <hi>them, who are ſanctified,</hi> becauſe <hi>it was offered by the Eternal Spirit.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9. 24.</note> 
               <hi>His Body is an Offering, a Sacrifice of an eternal ſweet-ſmelling</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 2.</note> 
               <hi>ſavour,</hi> becauſe he offer'd <hi>himſelf:</hi> now <hi>himſelf is God in our Nature;</hi> ſo the Offering is in the hand of Divinity. Thus his <hi>Blood offered by the Eternal Spirit purges the Conſcience from dead Works to ſerve the living God. The Blood of Chriſt, more precious than Silver or Gold, redeems from a vain Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation.</hi> All theſe are plain, and high Effects of a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Nature, and they are deriv'd from the <hi>humane Nature</hi> of Chriſt, call'd his <hi>Fleſh,</hi> his <hi>Body,</hi> his <hi>Blood,</hi> acted by an intellectual, holy, humane Soul, which <hi>delighted to do the Will of God,</hi> and <hi>the Law of God was within his heart.</hi> And <note place="margin">Pſal. 40. 8.</note> all this, by being in the hand of the Divinity of Jeſus Chriſt, is infinitely communicative both as to Time and Place.</p>
            <p>The Righteouſneſs of Angels, or of Men, though they had continued Holy as the ſtanding Angels, could not have done this: but what Chriſt the Lamb did, he did by the <hi>Eternal Spirit,</hi> which is infinite.</p>
            <p>Now theſe expiatory Extracts, Abſtracts drawn from the Body of Jeſus Chriſt, are ſo DIVINIZ'D, if I may ſo ſpeak, by the <hi>Eternal Spirit,</hi> That they are every where: Chriſt's Body, in this ſenſe, may be every where (even as his Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is,) with Pardon of Sin, Reconciliation to God, Peace with him, <hi>ſprinkling the Heart from an evil Conſcience;</hi> and all other great Effects: For, where is it that the Goſpel is, and true Chriſtians are, where this <hi>Propitiation</hi> for the Sins of the whole World is not? Where is it, that true Believers
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57608:15"/> in Jeſus Chriſt have not <hi>Right to eat of this Altar?</hi> And is not this <hi>Altar,</hi> as in a peculiar Inſtitution preſented in the <hi>Lord's Supper?</hi> Theſe Spirits may be extended any way, conveyed every way, not groſs <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> but theſe Divine, expiatory Extracts of the Body of Jeſus Chriſt, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended and applyed by the Divinity; the ſavour of that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, of that Sacrifice fills Heaven and Earth.</p>
            <p>From the <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> call'd the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cauſality </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt united to the <hi>Son of God,</hi> is drawn that common <hi>Image, Idea,</hi> and <hi>Exemplar,</hi> to which his Saints are every where <hi>Conform'd;</hi> They are <hi>Called, Justified,</hi> and <hi>Glorified</hi> according to this <hi>Image,</hi> for whom God did <hi>fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>know,</hi> He <hi>predeſtinated to be ſo Conform'd.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 29.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This is in all Nature, there is a common <hi>Idea</hi> and <hi>Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form</hi> of every kind of Being, and Life, and it is every where, as in the Mind, and under the Hand and Power of God; ſo that all in whatever parts of the World agree in it, each to their kind; And whatever is not form'd and ſhapen accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it, is monſtrous and miſ-ſhapen.</p>
            <p>So in Chriſt Jeſus, is depoſited, that common univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal <hi>Image,</hi> and <hi>Idea,</hi> according to which the <hi>New Creature</hi> is fram'd, and this is <hi>God manifeſted in the Fleſh,</hi> that <hi>He might be the Firſt Born among many Brethren:</hi> And this <hi>Image</hi> by the Divine Spirit is every where, and there is neither <hi>Jew</hi> nor <hi>Gentile, Scythian</hi> nor <hi>Barbarian, Bond</hi> nor <hi>Free;</hi> but <note place="margin">Col. 3. 11.</note> 
               <hi>all are one in Chriſt Jeſus. Called, Juſtified,</hi> as Chriſt was; <hi>Glorified,</hi> as He is, ſo ſhall they be; and particularly in the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> this <hi>Image</hi> is ſo preſented, that <hi>We are all one Bread, and one Body by being made partakers of that one</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Bread by Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this <hi>Image</hi> is not either a liveleſs or meer Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>Image,</hi> but it hath a mighty Power and Operation from the <hi>Spirit</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt to conform and configurate all his Servants to himſelf; That as He was in <hi>All Things made like unto his Brethren,</hi> ſo his <hi>Brethren</hi> are to Him. And this mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Aſſimilation is ſo cloſe, that <hi>He dwells in them, and they in Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:57608:15"/>
            <p> The <hi>Humane Nature</hi> of Chriſt hath therefore the Power <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cauſality </seg>3</label> of an unitive efficient Cauſe; for the <hi>Divine Spirit</hi> of Chriſt, by the Mediation of his <hi>Humanity,</hi> does unite himſelf to the Souls of his Servants, and ſo to their Bodies, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veys his Righteouſneſs in the value of his Blood, his Spirit in the power of Holineſs, that we become <hi>Members of his Body,</hi> his <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and his <hi>Bone;</hi> as <hi>Eve</hi> coming out of <hi>Adam</hi> and made <hi>one fleſh with him,</hi> was <hi>Fleſh of his Fleſh, Bone of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 30.</note> 
               <hi>his Bone:</hi> And ſo we are <hi>Branches</hi> of this <hi>Vine,</hi> of this <hi>Good</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Olive,</hi> who as a <hi>common Root beareth</hi> us All.</p>
            <p>So that indeed it comes to this, That all the Servants of Chriſt are as <hi>one Chriſt; for as the Body is one,</hi> and <hi>hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Members,</hi> and <hi>all the Members of that Body being many, are one Body; ſo alſo is Christ:</hi> As there are <hi>many Members,</hi> and <hi>one Body,</hi> juſt ſo is <hi>Christ,</hi> not <hi>Christ</hi> in his Perſon, but <hi>Christ</hi> in all his Members, <hi>All one Christ:</hi> So <hi>Galat.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>he ſaith not,</hi> Unto Seeds, as unto many, but as of one, To thy Seed; <hi>which is Christ, viz.</hi> Chriſt in his whole <hi>Body of Members. And we all come in the unity of the Faith of the Son of God unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the fullneſs of Christ,</hi> Chriſt full in all his Members: And the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> calls <hi>Jews and Gentiles, One new man in Christ;</hi> and the <hi>Church is the fullneſs of him that fills all in all:</hi> And thus we are one Body and one Bread. <note place="margin">Eph. 1. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>This is a <hi>great myſtery of Christ and the Church;</hi> but if rightly underſtood, it greatly explains Chriſt's Words, <hi>This is my Body:</hi> for as there are many Incorporations, as of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical Bodies, which are not loſt by diſtance of Place, as being Citizens of ſuch a City, myſtical as the Incorporation of <hi>Husband</hi> and <hi>Wife,</hi> which is not made void by diſtance of Place, while the Bands of Union hold; thus Chriſt in Heaven, by his Spirit, unites his Members to him on Earth; and his Body, in this ſpiritual ſenſe, is every where to be ſo joyn'd, and it does ſo draw to it ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:57608:16"/>
            <p> But this Union is yet more nearly expreſs'd by a natural Union, <hi>viz.</hi> by <hi>eating his Fleſh, and drinking his Blood,</hi> even as the <hi>Branches are united to the Vine, by being fed by the Vine,</hi> and ſucking from it; and ſo the Members are ſupplied with Spirits from the Head: and if they were not ſo, they would, notwithſtanding a local Union, be diſunited, as a withered Branch or Member is; even ſo by receiving the ſaving Effluxes and Communications of Jeſus Chriſt, which is an eating of him, <hi>we dwell in him, and he in us.</hi> And without this we are not united by any outward Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Duties.</p>
            <p>And this Union ſhall be moſt evident in the ſeparated ſtate of Souls, made like the Holy ſeparated Soul of Chriſt, or the <hi>Spirit</hi> of Chriſt <hi>committed into his Fathers Hand,</hi> and as it were all one Spirit, and are therefore, as <hi>Stephen</hi> was, receiv'd by him, and yet moſt viſible in the Reſurrection, when the Bodies of his Saints ſhall be made <hi>like his glorious Body,</hi> becauſe <hi>they ſhall ſee him as he is:</hi> for then indeed the <note place="margin">1 John 3. 2.</note> Body of Chriſt ſhall have a moſt natural Preſence and Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on the Bodies of Saints, and ſhall act properly, as mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon matter, or as the Sun upon the Moon and Planets about it, whoſe Bodies it illuſtrates. He will <hi>preſent his Church to himſelf</hi> then, <hi>without ſpot,</hi> or <hi>wrinkle,</hi> or <hi>any ſuch</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 21.</note> 
               <hi>thing,</hi> by <hi>that Power</hi> that <hi>ſubdues all things to himſelf. That</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Col. 3. 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Life that is now hid, as Chriſt is hid,</hi> ſhall then <hi>appear,</hi> and we ſhall <hi>appear with him in Glory,</hi> as all one Chriſt.</p>
            <p>He will then be as a Tree of Life, <hi>in the midſt of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe of God,</hi> and his Blood in a ſpiritual ſenſe, <hi>as a Water of Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And of this, the <hi>Lord's Supper</hi> is the great pledge, till <hi>He comes,</hi> and the Sacrament of <hi>Eating him,</hi> ſo as to live by him, and <hi>to be raiſed</hi> up by him at the laſt day when this Union ſhall fully appear.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Humanity</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, that is, His <hi>Body, Fleſh,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cauſality </seg>4</label> and <hi>Blood,</hi> as it is arrayed in the Holineſs, Heavenlineſs, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of it, and in that ſelf-Reſignation to the Will of God
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57608:16"/> in ſuffering, and becoming <hi>Obedient to Death, even to the Death of the Croſs,</hi> in higheſt love to loſt Sinners, is preſent every where in the Goſpel, every where ſet forth before our Eyes, <hi>Evidently Crucified among us.</hi> Galat. 3. 1.</p>
            <p>And this hath in all due Reaſon the force of a ſtrong and mighty Argument to draw us to him by Faith, and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to apply his Blood, and to Truſt in his Redemption, to move Chriſtians to the <hi>ſame Mind</hi> in every thing, that we ſee, <hi>was in Chriſt,</hi> it hath even a <hi>Conſtraining Power of love, to live to him that dyed for us, to purifie our ſelves, as he is Pure, to be in the World, as he was in the World, to Walk</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>as he Walked, to go out to him without the Camp of</hi> all Falſe Religions, out of the <hi>Camp</hi> of Senſuality, and Worldly-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, <hi>bearing his Reproach, to Crucifie the Fleſh with the Luſts, to be Crucified to the World, and the World to us, to ſet our Affections on things Above,</hi> Whither His Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture removed in regard of Place; But by the Preaching and Manifeſtation of the Goſpel, it is every where, as thus Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented, as thus ſet forth; This is a ſenſe of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, being every where, where his Goſpel and Word come, that cannot be denied; and as therein it is ſo receiv'd, as to become an Argument, and powerful mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of uniting our ſelves to Him of being like Him, It may be moſt ſignificantly expreſs'd by the Metaphor of <hi>Eating</hi> and <hi>Drinking,</hi> like <hi>Ezekiel's Eating the Roll, and filling his Bowels with it.</hi> This is a <hi>hearing Chriſt's Voice,</hi> which ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 20.</note> knocks or perſuades to <hi>open the Door to him;</hi> that he may, <hi>as he will, come in to Sup with us and we with Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a Senſe ſo proper and natural, that it is choſen by that <hi>Learned Interpreter, Grotius,</hi> to expound that great Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, <hi>John</hi> 6. <hi>of eating the Fleſh, and drinking the Blood,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Grot. in Evangel. John.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch a <hi>Receiving his Word</hi> and <hi>Sayings,</hi> as to be every way confirm'd in a way of Holy, Rational, Intellectual, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Obedience to Him.</p>
            <p>And, as there is ſo particular a Repreſentation of Jeſus Chriſt in the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> as a Sacrament ſumming up the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57608:17"/> whole Doctrine of the Goſpel, or of Jeſus Chriſt Crucified; ſo a particular <hi>Approbation</hi> of our ſelves to it, and for it, and the danger of an unworthy, an unbecoming <hi>Eating</hi> and <hi>Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> is ſo earneſtly and vehemently preſs'd upon us by the Apoſtle, as to infold us in the Guilt of his <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood, as if we had Crucified the Son of God afreſh,</hi> and <hi>put him to open Shame,</hi> and becauſe in the <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Times, the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> and the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the only two ſuch words in the New Teſtament.</note> 
               <hi>Lord's Day,</hi> the only Inſtitutions ſo inſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, were undivided; It was a Conſtant, Habitual, Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form Preparation that was required.</p>
            <p>Now that this is <hi>Eating and Drinking Chriſt</hi> in a myſtical Senſe agreeable to the Myſtery of the <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Supper</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, is very eaſie to be Apprehended, ſeeing Chriſt Jeſus is not to be lov'd, nor receiv'd in any Fleſhly Figure, He is no ſuch kind of Object to our Souls; even a virtuous Law-giver, or Philoſopher, is not to be lov'd in his Fleſh and Blood, as Groſs and Carnal, but, as in his Laws, his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, his Virtue, how much more Chriſt? <hi>If ye Love me, keep my Commandments:</hi> Pretend to no carnal Love, to no Love to me by looking on, and kiſſing my Pictures, or Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of fleſhly Repreſentations; <hi>For he that hath my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and keepeth them, he it is that loveth me, and he that thus loveth me, ſhall be loved of my Father,</hi> and I <hi>will</hi> 
               <note place="margin">John, 14. 15. 21. 23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>come to him, and manifeſt my ſelf to him: If a Man love me, he will keep my Sayings, and my Father will love him, and we will come unto him, and make our Abode with him;</hi> Words equal in Senſe to theſe, <hi>He that eateth my Fleſh, and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth my Blood, dwelleth in me, and I in him:</hi> On the other ſide, <hi>He that loveth me not, keepeth not my Sayings,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Whoever keepeth not my Sayings, loveth me not,</hi> All o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers attempt to do that, which cannot be done, to know and to <hi>love Christ after the Fleſh;</hi> whereas now there is no loving Chriſt, but in the <hi>New Creation, All old things are paſs'd away,</hi> Behold (mark it well) all Things are become new. All outward Repreſentations, Images, Pictures, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:57608:17"/> Geniculations, Adorations, if not commanded by him, are not the leaſt ſigns of Love, but rejected and refus'd by Chriſt, as a <hi>knowing him after the Fleſh;</hi> even the Ordinance <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5. 16.</note> of the <hi>Lord's Supper</hi> had been a falſe Love of Chriſt, if it had not been receiv'd from him, and ſpecially by himſelf commanded; and yet even as it is, without that ſpiritual Approbation, or approving our ſelves (which we tranſlate by the Word Examine our ſelves,) It is ſo far from Acceptance, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 28. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>it is eating and drinking Judgment to our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And all this is moſt rational, if we conſider, That we are our ſelves not truly our ſelves, but as we are thus intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually, ſpiritually, in a way of vertuous Conformity mov'd to things, by the great efficacy of Chriſt, and his Spirit in our Hearts, and move effectually by inward, rational Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion and Affection, according to the Arguments and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives in the Word of God, without which, we can under any Pretenſions, Profeſſions, Confeſſions of Faith, Forms of Worſhip, Prayers, outward Rites, Poſtures, and Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, be no more Chriſtians, than the Statues and Images of the Apoſtles or Saints are Chriſtians, becauſe they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd with ſuch Names, and vouch'd to be ſuch or ſuch Repreſentations.</p>
            <p>But when there is a ſingle Eye and Deſign to this Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the <hi>Word,</hi> and <hi>Sayings,</hi> and <hi>Commandments</hi> of Chriſt, there is then a far more real Preſence of Chriſt in his Word, than in any of the Writings or Lives of the moſt excellent Men that ever were in the World; for the Senſe and Reaſon they wrote are indeed here, their Actions and Vertues are drawn into Hiſtory, and may be preſerv'd from Copy to Copy, but the Soul, the Spirit that wrote them, is gone from them: but now Chriſt, <hi>yeſterday, to day, the ſame for ever,</hi> is preſent by that <hi>Spirit,</hi> that Divinity, by which <hi>he preach'd of old, even in</hi> Noah's <hi>Time to the diſobedient Spirits now in Priſon,</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 20. While his Truth operates after the manner of rational Truth, his Spirit works much higher, even divinely.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:57608:18"/>
            <p> His <hi>Table</hi> therefore in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and in his <hi>Supper,</hi> is a <note place="margin">Pſal. 28. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Table richly ſpread, a Cup running over</hi> with ſpiritual Effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, of which, whoever is indeed <hi>Partaker,</hi> cannot be a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of the <hi>Table of Devils,</hi> whoever truly <hi>drinks his Cup</hi> cannot drink of the <hi>Cup of Devils,</hi> either in an Idolatrous Religion, or an unholy Life: He cannot eat of the Sinners <hi>Dainties,</hi> of <hi>Folly's Bread,</hi> or of the ſtollen Waters <hi>ſhe hath</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 9. 17.</note> 
               <hi>provided.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For by one Offering he hath for ever perfected them that are ſanctified, of which the Holy Ghost is witneſs,</hi> even of that <hi>Covenant</hi> of which he is the <hi>Mediator, it being eſtabliſh'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the beſt Promiſes of writing the Laws of God in their hearts, and putting them in their mind,</hi> together <hi>with the Remiſſion of their Sins.</hi> So that as there needs no <hi>other offering</hi> than that <hi>one offering,</hi> ſo needs it not <hi>to be daily offered,</hi> for it was once for <hi>all offer'd,</hi> and he is now <hi>at the Right-hand of God</hi> interceeding upon that <hi>one offering, once offer'd;</hi> by the <hi>Blood</hi> of which he <hi>entred into the Holiest to appear before God</hi> for us, and from whence he cannot be mov'd till the Time <hi>he expects, of his Enemies being made his Footſtool,</hi> Heb. 8. 6. compar'd with <hi>c.</hi> 9. 12. 24. <hi>c.</hi> 10. 13. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And thus I have made good the firſt Point of this Head, <hi>viz.</hi> Of the ſpiritual Efficacies that flow from the Humane Nature of Chriſt, expreſs'd by the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, as in Union with the Son of God. I come now to the ſecond, to ſhew that in regard of the Eternity of the Son of God, theſe Efficacies cannot be hindered, nor pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judic'd in Point of Time: The Divine Perſon of Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unchangeable and eternal, there's no diſtance of Time occurs to him, or can encounter his Divine Efficacy: <hi>Before Abraham was,</hi> ſaith <hi>Christ, I am.</hi> How could it be, that Chriſt, that was born ſo many hundred years after <hi>Abraham,</hi> could be <hi>before Abraham?</hi> were it not in regard of the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Divine Perſon, communicated to the Humanity, and predating the Great Powers and Efficacies of <hi>God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted in Fleſh</hi> before the <hi>Incarnation?</hi> Upon this Account
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57608:18"/> Chriſt is call'd the <hi>Lamb ſlain before the Foundation of the World;</hi> becauſe the <hi>Divine Perſon</hi> anticipated the Efficacy of the Death of the <hi>Lamb, ordain'd before the Foundation of the World,</hi> much earlier than his Manifeſtation, which was not till the <hi>last Times:</hi> Chriſt was not abridg'd, nor fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall'd in Time, becauſe he did not actually dye till about four thouſand Years after the Fall of Man: for the <hi>Divine Perſon,</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, never had a <hi>Yeſterday,</hi> nor can have a <hi>To morrow,</hi> but is always in a <hi>To day, the ſame for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this very Point of <hi>Eating the Fleſh, and Drinking the Blood of Christ,</hi> when the Jews were ſo diſguſted with the Doctrine, Chriſt, to eaſe their Thoughts, propoſes his Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to their Conſideration, and ſhews the mighty ſpirituali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Power of the Divine Nature by it; <hi>What;</hi> ſaith he, <hi>if you ſhall ſee the Son of Man aſcend</hi> up where he was before: though he was as Man, the Son of not <hi>Fifty Years</hi> by many, as the <hi>Jews</hi> obſerv'd to him; yet he was in <hi>Heaven,</hi> as the <hi>Son of God,</hi> calling his Humanity, that was not actually till his Incarnation, as if it were.</p>
            <p>And as it is thus in regard of Time paſt, ſo in regard of Time to come, he ſaith, <hi>Lo I am with you to the End of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. In reſpect to Place, we ſhall find very great Expreſſions of the Divine <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>biquity,</hi> and <hi>Omnipreſence of the Son of God,</hi> extending the Manhood to all Spiritual Effects, without any Limitation, or Confinement within Place, though yet it be, according to its natural Preſence, determin'd to Place, even as the <hi>Incarnation</hi> it ſelf was to the <hi>Fullneſs of Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Saviour diſcourſing with <hi>Nicodemus</hi> upon the Point of Regeneration, <hi>John</hi> 3. 13. tells him, <hi>No Man hath aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended up to Heaven, but he that came down from Heaven, even the Son of Man, who is in Heaven:</hi> Obſerve it, Chriſt was in his Body upon Earth, His being the Son of Man was that to which his Body was proper, yet ſaith he, <hi>The Son of Man,</hi> that now diſcourſes thee upon Earth, This <hi>Son of Man is now in Heaven.</hi> How could this be, but only, becauſe no
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57608:19"/> ſpace does hinder or ſtraiten the ſpiritual Efficacy of the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity,</hi> or confine its Preſence, even as it is united to the <hi>Humanity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By all this you may ſee, Chriſt was in <hi>Heaven</hi> while he was <hi>upon Earth,</hi> and he was in <hi>Heaven</hi> before he was <hi>Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> for, <hi>He came down from Heaven;</hi> and all this by the Unchangeableneſs and the Omnipreſence of the Action of the <hi>Divinity</hi> united to the <hi>Humane Nature:</hi> and then as to his being now upon Earth, although the <hi>Heavens contain him,</hi> Conſider what the <hi>Apoſtle ſaith, He aſcended far above all Heavens,</hi> that <hi>he might fill all things:</hi> ſo that Chriſt, by his Divine Power, <hi>fills all things;</hi> and the <hi>Church,</hi> which is his <hi>Body</hi> in his <hi>Humane Nature</hi> on Earth, is the <hi>Fullneſs of him</hi> who <hi>filleth All in All;</hi> even he that was Raiſed up from the Dead, is he that <hi>fills All in All.</hi> And the <hi>Church</hi> on Earth is his Fullneſs, (though Chriſt is in Heaven) either receiving his <hi>Fullneſs,</hi> or, as he is pleas'd to account him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Full</hi> by his Union to it. Upon theſe Accounts, The <hi>Humane Nature</hi> of Chriſt, as it is united to <hi>the Divinity,</hi> though it ſelf be <hi>Finite,</hi> yet in the Extenſive Power of the <hi>Divinity,</hi> ſpiritually applying it to the Salvation of his <hi>Church,</hi> hath the Nature of <hi>Infinite:</hi> both as to Time and Place, it is always, it is every where, <hi>filling All in All, Yeſterday, to day, the ſame for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For if the Soul of Man can improve the Senſes, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of the Body, in repreſenting to it ſelf in a Map, Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces at greateſt Diſtances from the Body, and the Mind can thereby in ſome ſenſe convey it ſelf thither while the Body remains in the ſame place; If we can by Writing converſe one with another at greateſt diſtance, How much more can the <hi>Divine Nature</hi> of the Son of God extend the <hi>Humane</hi> in the Spirituality of all its Uſe and Effects, in an Infinite man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſo that it can convey and diſpoſe them unlimitedly as it pleaſes? and this may well be call'd his <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> in very real, though myſtical ſenſe.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:57608:19"/>
            <p> It remains yet, as to the clearing this Point of Chriſt <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his Fleſh to eat,</hi> and his <hi>Blood to drink,</hi> to ſhew, That as there is ſuch a rich Communicativeneſs on the part of Chriſt, giving his <hi>Fleſh to eat,</hi> and his <hi>Blood to drink;</hi> ſo there are Receiving Powers and Faculties of Man's Soul, prepared and fitted by Grace, that may be properly and truly ſaid, in a ſpiritual Senſe, to <hi>Eat,</hi> and to <hi>Drink,</hi> as Chriſt is ſaid to Give.</p>
            <p>Now unto this, the Underſtanding, Will, Conſcience, Memory, Imagination, and Affection, with the active and executive Powers of the whole Man, are prepar'd, even to receive ſpiritually the Fleſh and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever at a bodily diſtance; <hi>viz.</hi> by Underſtanding, Faith, cloſe inward Application, holy Affection, obediential ſelf-Reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; all which, are this Intellectual <hi>ſpiritual Eating</hi> and <hi>Drinking the Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And to all this, there is no Notion or Reſemblance more ſignificant or expreſſive than ſpiritual <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> as ſhall be more fully diſcours'd under the two following Heads: And ſo having thus far diſcuſs'd the firſt Head, I go forward to the ſecond, to ſhew, That there is a clear Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage and Tranſition from Chriſt giving his <hi>Fleſh to eat,</hi> (as it ſtands thus in the whole Doctrine of the Goſpel) to thoſe Words, <hi>Take, Eat, this is my Body,</hi> when he had <hi>bleſſed the Bread with Thanksgiving, and broke it;</hi> and likewiſe <hi>after Supper,</hi> Bleſſing the <hi>Cup,</hi> with Thankſgiving, and ſaying, <hi>Divide it among your ſelves, and drink ye All of it,</hi> For, <hi>This is my Blood of the New Teſtament,</hi> or <hi>the New Teſtament in my Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For when our Lord had ſettled that great Doctrine of <hi>Eating his Fleſh,</hi> John 6. <hi>and Drinking his Blood,</hi> compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive of the whole of his Redemption, and the ſaving Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of it by <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> and the entire <hi>new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Galat. 5. 6. c. 6. 15.</note> it is not at all ſtrange, he ſhould eſtabliſh ſo great a ſacramental Inſtitution upon it; For when in ſo large and Sublime a Diſcourſe, and in more Words, than he expended
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:57608:20"/> upon any one Subject that we find upon Record, he had compriz'd the whole Myſtery of our Salvation, it cannot be ſurprizing he ſhould adjuſt to it one of the two, and that the moſt ſolemn and continual of his poſitive Laws, which we call Sacraments.</p>
            <p>For though it is true, <hi>Eating</hi> and <hi>Drinking</hi> conſider'd, as mere ſenſitive Things, and much more, when it degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates into Senſuality, a Life of, and for Eating and Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it is a ſordid, low, and courſe thing, as the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>Meats for the Belly, and the Belly for Meats, but God ſhall deſtroy both it and them;</hi> and there cannot be a more ignoble Character, than of thoſe, whoſe <hi>God is their Belly,</hi> and who ſerve not the <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> but <hi>their own Bellies,</hi> a beaſtly, a bruitiſh Servitude.</p>
            <p>But then taking it, as it is by the Wiſdom of Providence made the means of the ſupport of the Humane, Animal Life, in Subordination to the Life of Reaſon and Religion, and is ſymbolical and ſignificant, and alſo ſerviceable to many rational Communications, and much noble Humanity of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, ſo it may even (as the natural Purgation of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in Baptiſm) be worthy to be tranſplanted from common uſe to the higheſt Significations in Religion, and as it had been ſo dignified in the Old Teſtament, ſo to be farther en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobled in the New, and to bear a ſenſe far above and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond it ſelf. And yet to ſhew both the Spirituality, great uſe to the higheſt Life, and alſo the Simplicity of the <hi>Goſpel Inſtitution,</hi> it is taken from the moſt neceſſary, plaineſt Food in Eating, <hi>Bread,</hi> and the moſt generous thing in Drinking, viz. <hi>Wine; Bread that ſtrengthens, and Wine that maketh glad the Heart of Man.</hi> And the Reſemblance ſtands in theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Particulars between <hi>Eating Bread</hi> and <hi>Drinking Wine,</hi> and <hi>Eating the Body,</hi> and <hi>Drinking the Blood of Jeſus Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I ſhall begin with thoſe Particulars that are, as leaſt of Controverſie, ſo of leaſt Intereſt in the main Merits of the Point we are upon, and will end in that which is of the grand Concern in this whole matter.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:57608:20"/> 1. It is an Eating and Drinking in Pledge of Reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Peace, and Friendſhip with God by Jeſus Chriſt; for ſo <hi>eating Bread</hi> and <hi>drinking Wine</hi> is in Scripture, and by the general Impreſſion of Providence upon Mankind ordain'd; as <hi>Joſeph's Brethren,</hi> in token of extraordinary Favour, were to eat Bread with him: and it is ſaid of the <hi>Nobles of Iſrael,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 43. 25.</note> They ſaw God, and he laid not his <hi>hand</hi> of, <hi>viz.</hi> of Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, upon them; They ſaw him, and <hi>did eat and drink</hi> in <note place="margin">Exod. 24. 11.</note> token of Peace; and eſpecially this is a Feaſt upon a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, a <hi>Sin-offering</hi> become a <hi>Peace-offering,</hi> of which the <hi>Jews,</hi> that <hi>ſerve the Altar,</hi> have <hi>no Right to eat,</hi> becauſe their <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 10.</note> Sin-offerings of greateſt expiatory Account, yet as not able to purge off the imputative Guilt laid upon them, were <hi>burnt without the Camp.</hi> But Chriſt, though he <hi>ſuffer'd without the Camp,</hi> yet conſuming the Guilt, and fully expiating it, <hi>his Body, as ſacrific'd,</hi> becomes an <hi>Altar of Peace-offerings</hi> to the true Chriſtian, although to the Jews an Offering only to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, not conquering the Guilt, but, as a Malefactor, dying in his own Blood: but the true Believer <hi>feasts</hi> upon it, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he is <hi>ſanctified,</hi> atton'd, reconcil'd, and purified by the <hi>Blood of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a Feaſt upon the <hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi> in aſſurance againſt the <hi>deſtroying Angel,</hi> the <hi>Blood</hi> being <hi>ſprinkled</hi> by way of <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5. 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>Expiation,</hi> and the <hi>Fleſh eaten</hi> in the way of a <hi>holy Feſtival,</hi> Rejoycing, and Thankſgiving.</p>
            <p>So that though <hi>eating the Fleſh of Christ</hi> carries a broad Signification of the great Evil, and Horror of Sin, and of the dreadful way of Reconciliation, looking ſo unnatural as the <hi>eating</hi> of the <hi>Fleſh</hi> and the <hi>drinking the Blood</hi> of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, does; yet by the great attoning vertue of this Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, it becomes a Feaſt of Joy and Peace.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Act is a ſolemn Act of Worſhip of God and Chriſt, <hi>We eat thus, and worſhip:</hi> It is an Acknowledgment of Jeſus Chriſt, as our Saviour, Lord, and Maſter, as all eating upon Sacrifices was an Acknowledgment of the God of the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: and ſeeing our Mediator is our Sacrifice, of whom it
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:57608:21"/> is teſtified, <hi>He lives for ever,</hi> and we are <hi>to live to him,</hi> it is an Acknowledgment of him our Saviour; and ſo it requires <hi>Reverence</hi> and <hi>Godly Fear,</hi> it calls for Self-probation even to <hi>Approbation,</hi> or <hi>Approvizing</hi> our ſelves, that <hi>ſo we may eat,</hi> and not otherwiſe. To <hi>eat</hi> and <hi>drink</hi> in a way <hi>worthy</hi> or becoming the <hi>Holy Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> we ſeed upon; to <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern that Body of the Lord,</hi> or to make a <hi>difference</hi> and <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimination</hi> betwixt it and all other <hi>Bread</hi> by ſpiritual, holy Action; and to carry from it ſuch Obligations as by no means to <hi>partake of the Table, or drink the Cup of Devils;</hi> This is the ſolemn Worſhip of Eating and Drinking be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Eating and Drinking is made a Symbol of Eternal Glory; for ſo Chriſt expreſſes Eternal Glory, by <hi>Eating and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luc. 22. 30. Matt. 8. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Drinking at his Table in his Kingdom. By ſitting down with</hi> Abraham, <hi>with</hi> Iſaac, <hi>and</hi> Jacob, <hi>in the Kingdom of God.</hi> And this is the Reaſon Chriſt, in that great <hi>Sixth</hi> of <hi>John,</hi> ſo often enterweaves with that Diſcourſe of <hi>Eating, Raiſing up at the last day;</hi> becauſe then ſhall the full effect of the Union to the Body of Chriſt be ſeen, when all his Members ſhall indeed be ſeen, as One Chriſt in Glory; Their Bodies ſhall be <hi>faſhioned like his Glorious Body; It does not yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear what we ſhall be,</hi> but when <hi>he ſhall appear we ſhall be like him, for we ſhall ſee him as he is. He will then preſent us fault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs before the Preſence of his Glory:</hi> And all this from the Power of Union to himſelf, through the <hi>eating his Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>drinking his Blood.</hi> So that Life, Eternal Life, <hi>Living for ever, Never dying, Raiſing up at the last Day, Having no Life</hi> if we do not <hi>eat the Fleſh of Christ,</hi> and <hi>drink his Blood,</hi> are in that Diſcourſe ſixteen Times mention'd, to ſhew how cloſe the Relation is betwixt <hi>eating the Fleſh of Christ,</hi> and <hi>drinking his Blood,</hi> and <hi>Eternal Life:</hi> So that the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſums up all the Diſcourſe in the Words of Eternal Life; <hi>Thou hast the Words of Eternal Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. I come now to the laſt and greateſt of thoſe Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances between the <hi>Fleſh</hi> or <hi>Body eaten,</hi> and Chriſt's <hi>Blood</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:57608:21"/> 
               <hi>drunk</hi> in the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> and natural Eating and Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>viz.</hi> Life and Nouriſhment; and this is that upon which the weight and ſtreſs of the whole matter lies: and in order to the underſtanding of this, it is moſt neceſſary well to weigh the Words, <hi>Take, Eat, This is my Body, And drink ye All,</hi> for <hi>This Cup is my Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For here the Notion of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> hath the moſt proper place, and here it will be moſt properly to be deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: and here I will allow the utmoſt to it that can be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed.</p>
            <p>I have then, as I hope, made evident, The real Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood of Jeſus Christ,</hi> in its ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, ſaving, and redemptory Effects, without any change of Place, is no incompoſſible Notion, to the Divine Power of the Son of God: And this being rightly apprehended, It will be as evident, He can convey through ſuch mediatory Channels and Conveyances (as he pleaſes) thoſe divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences. It is out of all Controverſie, The Truth of his Word and Goſpel, together with Prayer and holy Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, begetting in the Soul, Knowledge, ſpiritual Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, Faith, Repentance, Love, and the whole <hi>New Creation,</hi> are the primary and fundamental Conveyances of ſuch divine Influences, by which the ſacred <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt touch the Soul, and unite with it, unto all the ſalvifick Effects of Spiritual and Eternal Life.</p>
            <p>And the very effects of Truth, and the Word of God, uniting the Soul to Chriſt, through the Efficacy of his Divine Power and Spirit, are in the firſt place, before the <hi>Lord's Supper Inſtituted,</hi> compar'd to Meat and Drink.</p>
            <p>And as They, in the Courſe of that Providence, or Word of God, by which <hi>Man lives,</hi> and not by Bread alone, are <hi>Tranſubſtantiated</hi> into the <hi>Body, Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of thoſe that Eat and Drink them; even ſo the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> in theſe ſaving Effects, are <hi>Tranſubſtantiated</hi> into the Soul and Spirit of every faithful Receiver of them, and enliven them to a ſpiritual and eternal Life: and there
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:57608:22"/> can be no fitter Notion of theſe Divine Effects than this <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> of natural Meat and Drink, and Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration thereof into the Eater: for even as what is eaten ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the nature of Periſhables lives in the Eater, dwells in the Eater, and he in that, and they are one in one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; even ſo they that Eat Chriſt, <hi>dwell in Christ, and Christ in them.</hi> Chriſt lives in his Church and Saints, out of which he is pleas'd not to live, as our Mediator and Head: But he lives in them as in his Fullneſs, and they in him, as in their Fountain of Life; <hi>Christ in them,</hi> and They in him by this ſpiritual <hi>Tranſubſtantiation;</hi> or elſe they <hi>have no life in them,</hi> but pine away as through want of Nouriſhment.</p>
            <p>This then being the true meaſure of <hi>eating</hi> and <hi>drinking Christ,</hi> and the ſpiritual <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> ariſing from it, as in the general Doctrine of the Goſpel, it muſt give Law and Rule to our <hi>eating</hi> and <hi>drinking of Christ</hi> in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> that we may rightly underſtand it, and ſo to the <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> flowing from it: It muſt be all in our ſpiritual Transformation into Chriſt living in us, and we in him, and no other in that principal Notion.</p>
            <p>But becauſe in all Intellectual and Spiritual Communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Truth to our Minds, there are no ſenſible, no mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Images or Repreſentations, and that by the Wiſdom of Jeſus Chriſt in the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> there are thoſe ſenſible Images of <hi>Bread eaten</hi> and <hi>Wine drunk,</hi> and theſe Cargoed and enrich'd with the Repreſentation of the <hi>Body and Blood of Jeſus Christ;</hi> and that theſe are to awaken, collect, and ſum all our intellectual, rational, and ſpiritual Notions of Chriſt, the Vertue of his Sacrifice, and whole Tranſaction of the Humane Nature, and our cloſeſt Application there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, as to our Redemption by him.</p>
            <p>It muſt needs therefore be, that the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> as to our Underſtandings, our Souls, and all intellectual and ſpiritual Appetite and Action, having done their very firſt Service of leading us through the whole ſuitableneſs betwixt <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> and the natural Life of Man, and the ſame ſuitableneſs betwixt the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:57608:22"/> and the Life of the Soul, according to the Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they muſt immediately drop their bodily and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Nature, and become to our Minds, Thoughts, and Affections the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood of Christ.</hi> And it pertains to the Divine Power of Jeſus Chriſt, and his <hi>Eternal Spirit,</hi> to make, in a ſpiritual Reality, that <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> his very <hi>Body and Blood,</hi> in all its Efficacies, to us, if we are duely prepar'd ſo to receive them: And the inward, high, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Effects, to all Intents and Purpoſes, immediately follow.</p>
            <p>But yet if the true natural Realities of theſe Elements, or the ſubſequent unitive Incorporating Vertues of thoſe Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were loſt, not only the Inſtitution it ſelf, founded on thoſe ſenſible Qualities, would be loſt, but the very <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Chriſt, by ſuch a monſtrous kind of Miracle, would become <hi>outward Elements to themſelves;</hi> for, by the very Confeſſion of the groſs <hi>Tranſubſtantialist,</hi> They, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>Tranſubſtantiated,</hi> do no good without Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and ſo do no more than the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntranſubſtantiated Bread and Wine</hi> may do, and ſo prodigious a Miracle ſerves to no purpoſe, which is moſt abſurd; For it makes the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> mere outward Elements to themſelves.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> then muſt, as to the bodily Senſes, as to the natural Effects upon the Body, be Themſelves, or keep their own Natures; but as to the ſpiritual Sentiments, and the ſpiritual Effects, they muſt be thus <hi>Tranſubſtantiated into the Body and Blood of Cbrist,</hi> in regard of Chriſt really communicating them by his divine Power to the Soul, as the Soul by Faith muſt receive them.</p>
            <p>There muſt therefore be the Conduct of all the <hi>Inſtituted</hi> Actions, <hi>Bleſſing, Breaking, Taking, Eating, the Bread; Bleſſing, Dividing among our ſelves,</hi> Drinking, All, of the CUP, and that in a ſolemn manner, as in an Act of ſpiritual Worſhip, with Reverence and godly Fear; elſe <hi>it is not to eat the Lord's Supper:</hi> for, If a Prieſt, not rightly ordain'd, or not intending to conſecrate the Bread, ſhall in the very Judgment of the <hi>Tranſubſtantialiſt</hi> defeat the ſacred Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:57608:23"/> how much more ought, in the very ſame mens Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the Neglect or Omiſſion of any of the ſolemn Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted Acts evacuate the ſpiritual uſe and end of which the natural uſe of the <hi>Bread and Wine,</hi> (neceſſarily to that end continuing in their Natures) was one great part; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, undoubtedly, if the Stomachs of Communicants were open'd, as <hi>Alexander</hi> open'd the Stomach of his Souldier, to find whether the Milk charg'd upon him to be taken away from the poor Woman by violence, were there, and there he found it; ſo the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> would be found in the Stomach of the freſh Communicant, making the juſt natural Progreſſes, and moves to Union, Incorporation, and Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment, that according to the Law of ſubſtantial Food (not Accidents) or according to Nature, it ſhould do.</p>
            <p>And it is neceſſary it ſhould be ſo, that the <hi>ſpiritual Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation</hi> may anſwer the Reſemblance Chriſt hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen for it, and might guide us into the underſtanding of it, and Application of our Souls to it, according to the ſteps of the natural Converſion of Food into our Fleſh, and Blood, and Life; yet not ſo that Chriſt ſhould be obliged to his own Ceremonies, as if he could not work without them.</p>
            <p>But this is the ordinary means, even beſides and beyond the Word, that the Goodneſs of Chriſt hath choſen, that we might have the moſt ſenſible and powerful Application of our Souls to him, and of him to our Souls in ſuch a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which hath, beſides the very Time of Celebration, [even in caſes of Omiſſion by neceſſary Impediment,] its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant uſe; for, the Ordination it ſelf is a Seal, always and inſeparably faſten'd to God's Covenant, and does aſſure the great Point of the real Exhibition of Chriſt to the Faith of his Servants, as ſubſtantially, as the Meat and Drink we live by, aſſures it ſelf to our Bodies and Senſes, and this always.</p>
            <p>And this Offer, this Exhibition, is ſo real, that whoever profeſſing the Goſpel, and having the Knowledge of this Sacramental Inſtitution, and eſpecially coming to the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> and not approving himſelf in all the ſpiritual Acts of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:57608:23"/> receiving Chriſt, <hi>becomes guilty of the Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of the Lord. Now as we know this Guilt is only of a ſpiritual Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, committed againſt the Body and Blood of Chriſt thus ſpiritualiz'd in their effects, for who can hurt Chriſt's natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Body in Heaven? ſo it aſſures us, the Preſence of the Body and Blood is only of a ſpiritual Nature, and ſo the Tranſubſtantiation is only ſpiritual; for as the Guilt is, ſo is the Preſence: and if the Preſence were ſenſible, the Guilt might be by an Injury of a ſenſible, Nature: but we know, It is not ſo; and ſo the Preſence and Sin alſo muſt be of a ſpiritual Nature.</p>
            <p>And ſo alſo is the Sin of not <hi>diſcerning,</hi> of not <hi>diſcrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating the Lord's Body.</hi> It muſt needs be the Sin of the Mind, becauſe there is no Preſence that ſtrikes the Senſe; The Senſe is in no Fault, for there is no <hi>Body</hi> of Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it; but the Mind, that does not <hi>diſcern,</hi> is to be blam'd: for that hath a high, ſpiritual Object, made known to it, <hi>evidently ſet before it</hi> by the <hi>Word</hi> of Chriſt, in the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> but only to it, not to the bodily eye or ſenſe: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Preſence can be only ſpiritual.</p>
            <p>But ſo certain as the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> are preſent to the Senſe, ſo certain are the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Chriſt, in a <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> For it muſt be acknowledg'd, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> ſtanding in a <hi>Sacramental,</hi> ſolemn <hi>Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> is of greater force than a mere metaphorical Saying, <hi>I am the Vine,</hi> and does ſignifie a Preſence of Chriſt with the <hi>Bread,</hi> in ſuch a manner, that the General Doctrine of the Goſpel concerning the real Communication of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Chriſt in general, is more particularly determin'd to the <hi>Bread, Bleſſed,</hi> and <hi>Broken, Taken</hi> and <hi>Eaten,</hi> which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Memorial perpetually annex'd to the Goſpel by Chriſt's Inſtitution, and is a Superaddition of the Certainty of a real, ſpiritual Preſence, of all the ſaving Effects of the <hi>Body and Blood of Christ,</hi> in the manner before diſcours'd: And the Guilt of <hi>unworthy</hi> Receiving, or not <hi>diſcriminating</hi> this <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> is proportionally a Sin committed
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:57608:24"/> againſt the ſpiritual Preſence of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> there repreſented, in all its ſpiritual Effects, and really, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially, though by Divine Abſtraction and Infinite Diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of them, without any material bodily Preſence.</p>
            <p>And though this Sin, according to the Laws of Diſcourſe, is charg'd only upon the <hi>unworthy Eating</hi> and <hi>Drinking,</hi> as at <hi>the Table of Chriſt,</hi> in a ſet Diſcourſe of the <hi>Sacrament;</hi> yet, as the Divine <hi>Inſtitution</hi> offers at all Times the <hi>Body and Blood of Chriſt,</hi> and teſtifies the Truth of a real Participati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt by the True Believer; ſo the Obligation, and conſequently the Guilt, is chargeable upon every Pretender to Chriſt, whether he be a Receiver or not, as is moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. all along the Chapter. And ſuch a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanation of the <hi>Lord's Supper</hi> as the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were guilty of, as even the turning it into a Riot and Revel, ſo that <hi>it was not to Eat the Lord's Supper;</hi> yet the weight of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution</hi> fell upon them, even as it does upon all, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanely forbear the <hi>Lord's Supper</hi> among us, [as it were in their own Defence, againſt the Danger of it;] whoſe Guilt is the ſame as to the not Receiving Chriſt exhibited to them in the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> that muſt be always <hi>Preach'd,</hi> as a <hi>Memorial</hi> of Chriſt <hi>Inſtituting</hi> it, wherever <hi>this Goſpel is preach'd,</hi> and is pretended to be ſo Receiv'd by All, that is by all who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be Chriſtians: So that they do not, by neglect, leſſen the Guilt of an <hi>unworthy Eating</hi> and <hi>Drinking,</hi> which the very Profeſſion of Chriſtianity entitles them to, but alſo add that of a profane Omiſſion and Neglect of ſo Holy an <hi>Inſtitution.</hi> Now as all this is moſt evident by a Collation of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle's Diſcourſe, in the fore-mention'd Chapters, ſo it is of <note place="margin">1 Cor. c. 10.</note> great Illuſtration to the Point we are upon, as alſo Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of careleſs profane Chriſtians, who muſt, whether they will or no, be under the Bond of this Covenant, to whom Chriſt is ſo clearly ſet forth before their Eyes, and no Shift can diſoblige them.</p>
            <p>I come therefore to the Third Head of this Diſcourſe, <hi>viz</hi> To find a fair Accommodation, and no Encounter betwixt <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Head </seg>3</label>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:57608:24"/> the Myſtery and the Letter, or betwixt the grand Senſe and the very Words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> by a compare of this whole Harmonical Context with other Scripture, and its way of ſpeaking in ſuch Caſes.</p>
            <p>And in this I have ſo far prevented my ſelf, that there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains nothing, but to gather up the whole Context, and then to apply to it the ſenſe of this <hi>Myſtery</hi> I have purſued: Whereupon it will be evident, theſe Words, <hi>This is my Body, This is my Blood,</hi> agree with the conſtant manner of Scriptures ſpeaking in ſuch Matters, and that leſs than theſe Words could not import the great Senſe that was to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported.</p>
            <p>It is therefore firſt to be conſider'd, That Jeſus Chriſt our Lord and Saviour, even <hi>the very night he was betray<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d to dye,</hi> that he might draw up the whole Myſtery of Redemption in ſhort, and into a Sum; He does it firſt in that moſt ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, typical, ſacrifical Rite of the <hi>Paſſover,</hi> that had been of ſo great uſe and ſignification in the Church of God among the <hi>Jews;</hi> of which, the ſeveral Ordinances for the ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it bound together, are call'd by not a Literal, but Myſtical Propriety, the <hi>Lord's Paſſover.</hi> Exod. 12. 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Paſſover, with Deſire, Chriſt deſir'd to eat with his Diſciples, before he ſuffer'd,</hi> as a very lively Table of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demptional Suffering, ſo near: but withal, He declares, <hi>He would no more Eat of it, till it was fulfill'd in the Kingdom of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Immediately upon this, whether out of an appendant Rite to the <hi>Paſſover,</hi> or not, is not now material, He <hi>Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes the Lord's Supper,</hi> as it were <hi>proleptically,</hi> and by way of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and yet Intuition, and looking upon his Death juſt before him, and draws in this new Table the Intention of it: but whether it was to be celebrated any more, there is no Explicite, but that Implicite Preception. In the <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelist Luke, Do it in Remembrance of me;</hi> which carries an Intimation of a Continuation: but it is obſervable, It is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied only <hi>to the Bread,</hi> importing the <hi>Body of Chriſt:</hi> and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:57608:25"/> it abates much from the rigour of a groſs, carnal Senſe, where it ſeems to preſs hardeſt. For as to the <hi>Wine</hi> being materially the <hi>Blood of Christ,</hi> that Figure, <hi>This Cup,</hi> for this Wine in the Cup; and that variation [is <hi>the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in my Blood]</hi> does, beyond all Contradiction, rebate the groſs Literal Senſe, even as <hi>Remembrance</hi> does from <hi>[This is my Body;]</hi> for Remembrance is of Abſent, and not Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; This therefore was as before-hand to an after thing; So Chriſt ſaid of the <hi>Body [which is broken]</hi> although it was not yet actually <hi>broken,</hi> and of the <hi>Blood [which is ſhed]</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it was not then <hi>ſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Immediately after the drinking of the <hi>Wine,</hi> Chriſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd, <hi>I will no more drink of This Fruit of the Vine, till I drink it new in the Kingdom of God my Father,</hi> when it comes; which to ſhew a thing of weight, and of the ſame Senſe <hi>with eating the Paſſover no more till,</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt Luke</hi> is before-hand with the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of the Cup, to joyn to that Saying of the <hi>Paſſover,</hi> this, <hi>of the Fruit of the Vine,</hi> as is very viſible.</p>
            <p>And both theſe Expreſſions ſpeak theſe three Things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there was an eminent <hi>Kingdom of God the Father</hi> immediately to ſucceed, at whoſe <hi>Right-hand Chriſt ſits till</hi> the Time of his own peculiar <hi>Kingdom</hi> comes, which is not till <hi>he puts down all Rule,</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> and laſt of all <hi>aboliſhes Death</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> out of <hi>God's Creation,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Lake,</hi> its own Place, which is the <hi>Second Death,</hi> or <hi>the Death of Death,</hi> and then he reſigns back <hi>the Kingdom.</hi> The Kingdom of God and Chriſt are thus kept diſtinct, and the <hi>Kingdom of the Father</hi> is in an eſpecial manner the ſtate of the Goſpel, after the <hi>Reſurrection, Aſcenſion, Sitting of Chriſt at his Right-hand,</hi> and his <hi>continual Interceſſion</hi> even untill that <hi>Glorious Kingdom of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Death of Jeſus Chriſt, imported in both the <hi>Paſſover</hi> and the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> was to be renewed into a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Life and Vertue immediately after his Death, by thoſe his <hi>Reſurrection, Aſcenſion, Seſſion on God's Right-hand,</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:57608:25"/> and <hi>Interceſſion,</hi> which are the <hi>Goſpel-Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That Chriſt, in a ſpiritual ſenſe, continually <hi>eats the Paſſover,</hi> as <hi>fulfill'd in the Kingdom of God,</hi> drinks <hi>the Wine</hi> as <hi>new in the Kingdom of God,</hi> and that with his <hi>Diſciples</hi> of all Ages, <hi>viz.</hi> in that perpetual Renovation of his <hi>Death</hi> in his <hi>Interceſſion,</hi> and Application of the Benefits thereof to Believers, according to the whole Tenor of the Goſpel, and particularly of the <hi>Lord's Supper;</hi> and as in a <hi>Pro-gramma</hi> or afore-hand Portraicture of all this, thoſe excellent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of at leaſt <hi>John</hi> 15. <hi>c.</hi> 16. and that great Prayer, a Pattern of the Interceſſion of Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 17. following ſhew.</p>
            <p>And of this <hi>Interceſſion of Christ</hi> upon his own <hi>Death,</hi> the <hi>Lord's Supper</hi> is in higheſt ſenſe the <hi>Memorial;</hi> for, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of Chriſt is not of a <hi>dead Christ,</hi> but who <hi>lives for ever,</hi> to make <hi>Interceſſion,</hi> and <hi>ſo ſaves to the uttermost.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In conſequence of all this, eſpecially the <note n="*" place="margin">A point moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the Apoſtles <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> (I had almoſt ſaid ſolely by them) <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. Epiſt. to the <hi>Heb.</hi> frequently and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly, <hi>c.</hi> 7. the Apoſtle <hi>John c.</hi> 15, <hi>c.</hi> 16. <hi>c.</hi> 17. eſpecially <hi>Epiſt. c.</hi> 2. 1, 2.</note> Interceſſion of Chriſt, The Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> as a <hi>fourth Evangelist,</hi> concerning this <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> is immediately commiſſion'd by Chriſt from Heaven, to promulge it to all Ages of Chriſtians. And therein he reveals it under a ſolemn new Title, as it were <hi>new in the Kingdom of God.</hi> The <hi>Lord's Supper.</hi> He applies to it its great Scope and End, both to the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>to the Wine;</hi> Do it in ſolemn Memorial of Chriſt, and his Action now in Heaven upon his <hi>Death</hi> which was here on Earth: and farther in thoſe Words; <hi>You ſhew forth his Death till he comes,</hi> that is, the whole Contexture of his Death, as <hi>his Body is eaten</hi> and <hi>his Blood drunk</hi> through the Efficacy and Application of his <hi>Interceſſion,</hi> through which we <hi>offer the Sacrifice of Praiſe, giving Thanks to his Name,</hi> through him, in this <hi>Eucharist</hi> or <hi>Feast of Thankſgiving,</hi> of whoſe <hi>Altar</hi> we continually <hi>Eat,</hi> even that of the <hi>Great Shepheard of the Sheep brought again from the Dead by the Blood of the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Covenant,</hi> as the Apoſtle hath moſt divinely woven theſe Things into a Neighbourhood, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>v.</hi> 20.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:57608:26"/>
            <p> And this <hi>Ordinance,</hi> with this whole State of Things, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> hath dated till <hi>the Coming of Christ,</hi> when a new State ſhall receive this into it ſelf, till which this <hi>Ordinance</hi> cannot be ſuperannuated, or out of Date; for which his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>receiv'd into Glory</hi> is poſtpond in the <hi>Myſtery of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> that it may be a Pawn and Pledge of his Kingdom of Glory. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16. on which the Apoſtaſie follows, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all till then. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>Laying then all theſe Things together, how evident is it, This whole Matter is of a divine, ſpiritual, heavenly Senſe? and therefore the <hi>Words</hi> concerning it are to be underſtood <hi>myſtically, ſpiritually, heavenly,</hi> however expreſs'd in a Phraſe and Language neareſt, moſt eaſie, and familiar to Senſe, by which Senſibleneſs, the Subſtantialneſs, Reality, certain Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of thoſe Spiritualities is to be underſtood; and yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be detracted, or derogated from the Spirituality: and to interpret otherwiſe, is to go contrary to the Rule of all Language, and of Scripture-Language particularly, and is as miſchievous as the worſt ſort of Allegorizing, or Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuating the ſenſe of the Letter of Scripture, where plain <hi>hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorical</hi> Things are intended. The one is turning <hi>Scripture</hi> into a <hi>ſpiritual Romance,</hi> the other is to ſubvert the whole World of <hi>Spirituals,</hi> to bring in horrible <hi>Anthropomorphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> or imagining God to have <hi>Eyes, Hands, Feet,</hi> &amp;c. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Scripture repreſenting the Reality of his divine Action, Providence and Government does it in Words and Images we beſt underſtand; and in a word, to bring in rank <hi>Hob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bianiſm</hi> into the Scripture, the Church of God, and into this <hi>Sacrament,</hi> as ſhall be more particularly remark'd under a following Head.</p>
            <p>Add hereunto, This is moſt particularly the Language of Scripture in <hi>Sacramental</hi> or <hi>Teſtamentary</hi> Diſcourſes, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes concerning the <hi>Covenant,</hi> according to that famous Inſtance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 19. 20. <hi>When</hi> Moſes <hi>had ſpoken every Precept to the People, according to the Law, he took the Blood of Calves, of Goats, with Scarlet-wool and Hyſop, and ſprinkled both the</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:57608:26"/> 
               <hi>Book, and the People,</hi> ſaying, upon the whole, <hi>This Thing, this whole Thing, is the Blood of the Covenant, which God hath enjoyn'd you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>Bread, Bleſſed, Broken, Taken, Eaten,</hi> is the Body of Chriſt, (and proportionably the Blood.) This whole Thing, the whole <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> of the Goſpel, always <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> conſider'd and embrac'd firſt, and then the <hi>Bread,</hi> ſo <hi>Bleſſed, Broken, Taken, Eaten,</hi> is the Body of Chriſt; and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly this <hi>Cup</hi> or <hi>Wine</hi> particularly <hi>Bleſſed, Divided, Drunk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that not only in a figurative, cold ſacramental, or commemorative Senſe; for that <hi>Divine Power,</hi> that <hi>Eternal Spirit of Christ,</hi> does infinitely propagate the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, repreſenting his whole Humanity, in all the ſaving Efficacies and mighty Effects proper thereunto; as perpetually in the Doctrine and Truth of the Goſpel, in an intellectual way, ſo in this Supper, as in a ſenſible mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Repreſentation; but yet only confirming, aſſuring, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king preſent a divine ſpiritual Efficacy, as hath been all along declar'd: And even as the Bread and Wine have an undoubted evident Appearance to Senſe, are Eaten, Taſted, Concocted in the Stomach, converted into Fleſh, Blood, and Spirits; ſo are the <hi>Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt</hi> really preſent in the <hi>Bread,</hi> in the <hi>Wine, viz.</hi> in their ſpiritual Effects, juſtly called <hi>his Body</hi> and <hi>Blood:</hi> So that the <hi>Bread</hi> is in true ſpiritual Senſe the <hi>Body of Christ,</hi> to be eaten ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually, to be taſted ſpiritually, to be turn'd into ſpiritual <hi>Life</hi> to the Soul, in which <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> go hand in hand with the Elements, in all their natural Progreſs, by their Spirituality: and ſo that the want of due ſpiritual Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all that profeſs Chriſt Jeſus, whether at, or not at the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> (however particularly applied to that) is an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt the very <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, and brings a Guilt proportionable to the Offence; All which hath the Full of a ſpiritual <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> and is the Thing we have purſued.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:57608:27"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Head </seg>4</label> I am come down now to the fourth Head, <hi>viz.</hi> To en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into this Thing, How there came into the Chriſtian Church ſuch a Notion as that <hi>Fleſhly Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> ſo earneſtly contended for. And I account it to theſe four Cauſes:</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cause </seg>1</label> That this Great and Excellent Doctrine of the Goſpel, eſpecially in that ſo often magnified <hi>Sixth</hi> of <hi>John,</hi> and in the <hi>Inſtitution of the Lord's Supper,</hi> give great Warranty to obſerve a great and <hi>divine Myſtery</hi> in the <hi>Goſpel</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, and in his <hi>Supper:</hi> That there muſt be ſome real ſenſe of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, as preach'd in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> as preſented in the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated ſo, as to be <hi>Meat</hi> and <hi>Drink</hi> indeed, and to <hi>give Life</hi> to our Souls.</p>
            <p>All this <hi>Myſtery</hi> cannot be exhauſted, and drawn out in no more than a plain Aſſent to this, that Chriſt dyed as an Attonement for the World, (if ſo much be allowed as <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianiſm</hi> denies,) and gave a Body of Holy Precepts and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, of an excellent Nature; and that whoever lives in Obedience to theſe, with Sincerity, ſhall have that their Obedience imputed to them for Righteouſneſs, through the <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> and <hi>juſtifie</hi> Men, as perfect and unſinning Obedience ſhould have been and done by the <hi>firſt Covenant with Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rationaliſts and Moraliſts draw down this Goſpel-Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry too low, while they ſeem to acquit themſelves to Reaſon and general Underſtanding, and to carry all Things plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly before that, They loſe the high Spirituality of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity; which they are too ready to eſteem no better than <hi>Jargon Cant,</hi> and Non-ſenſe. There is a Goſpel middle betwixt groſs, portentous, carnal <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> and ſuch an emaciating and ſhrinking up the great and unſearchable Treaſures of the Goſpel, as if they did not much excell a Lecture out of <hi>Plato, Plutarch, Epictetus,</hi> or ſome of the great <hi>Sages</hi> of Morality; joyn'd to ſome Articles of Faith and Forms of Worſhip.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:57608:27"/>
            <p> The way and manner of the Goſpel ſpeaking of theſe things, and eſpecially as <hi>our Lord and Saviour ſpake, who ſpake as never man ſpake,</hi> might well raiſe the Minds of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to look for ſomething high, and ſurpaſſing in the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Chriſtian Religion, and beyond common Senſe, or common Reaſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Many of thoſe we call the <hi>Antients,</hi> or <hi>Fathers,</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out of the Heathen Learning and Eloquence, into the Profeſſion of Chriſtianity, Men of great Holineſs, Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and Sanctity of Converſation, Contempt of the World, Readineſs to dye for the Name of Chriſt, and generally <hi>Martyrs,</hi> of curious and delicate Reaſon, of very ſublime Notion and Sentiments, of a flowing Language, ſoftneſs and ſweetneſs of Speech, and accompliſh'd with all the Graceful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of Rhetorick, taking the Scripture-Expreſſions, and diſplaying upon them with that Magnificency and Gallantry of Words, and all kind of Wit, but not purſuing ſtrongly and cloſely the Reaſon, Strength, and whole <hi>Analogy</hi> of Scripture, nor guarding their Diſcourſe by a Nervous <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare of Scripture with Scripture,</hi> launch'd out into many free and liberal Expreſſions concerning theſe Things, which not ballanc'd, limited, defended againſt poſſible Miſtake, at ſome Times, and in ſome Veins of their Writings in this Matter, might give occaſion to the more grievous and dreadful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes to ſuch a courſe of Times, as we may eaſily obſerve ſucceeded them.</p>
            <p>And this they did at the higher rate, undoubtedly, out of a great Zeal for the Honour of Chriſtian Religion; for, the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Pagans</hi> ſpeaking high of their <hi>Cabalaes, Great Myſteries,</hi> and Secrets of Religion, and their <hi>Myſtae,</hi> who had the guard of theſe <hi>Myſteries,</hi> their <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toes.</hi> The Fathers of the Chriſtian Church, knowing the true Excellency of <hi>Divine Myſteries,</hi> and pitching upon this, as eaſily the moſt remarkable, <hi>viz.</hi> the Doctrine <hi>of eating the Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>drinking the Blood of Chriſt;</hi> and this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in an eſpecial manner conſigned into the <hi>Myſtery of</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:57608:28"/> 
               <hi>the Lord's Supper,</hi> to which is adjoyn'd that ſevere Diſcourſe of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. It was very obvious to them, here eſpecially, to exalt the Glory of Chriſtianity, and of the holy Miniſters of it, as highly ſurmounting the Poor, if true, but therefore moſt poor, becauſe falſe Myſteries of outdated <hi>Judaiſm,</hi> and much more of <hi>Paganiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is moſt evident, at the very ſame Time, in the very ſame Places of their Writings, they in the ſame kind of flowing Eloquence intermix other Expreſſions, that ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently argue, How free they were from any Miſapprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in theſe Things: But their way of Writing being not by way of ſevere Examination of Scripture Notions and Texts, not by the auſtere Beam of Scripture, in its ſeveral Portions of <hi>Revealed Truth,</hi> and of the <hi>Sacred Context,</hi> nor having any ſurmiſe of the after danger, there being ſo little occaſion, or appearance of Fear at the Time, left Things ſo, as that the following Times deprav'd their Innocent Glory of Learning, and ſublime Ingeny, dyed deep with Love of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Through the many Devaſtations of the Chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, by the Barbarous Nations, by the <hi>Saracens,</hi> and <hi>Turks,</hi> in a long Tract of Time, through the daily Decay of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Knowledge, Zeal, and Holineſs, there enſued a great Darkneſs, Ignorance, Barbariſm, upon the Chriſtian World; in which, Men of the beſt Note ſeiz'd upon ſuch Expreſſions of <hi>Scripture,</hi> and the <hi>Fathers,</hi> whoſe <hi>Sepulchres they built,</hi> and <hi>garniſhed their Tombs</hi> all manner of ways, (I add no more) and it may be, as it ſeem'd to them moſt to make for the Honour of Chriſtian Religion: But their Underſtanding being heavy, courſe, ſinking into the thick and impure matter, bearing alſo a deep Grain of <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> they grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly <hi>err'd,</hi> neither <hi>knowing the Scriptures,</hi> the true Senſe of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> nor <hi>of the Power of God;</hi> And hereunto they proportion'd all their Notions of the Chriſtian Religion, their Worſhip of God and Chriſt, and moſt miſerably eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, They ſtuck in the <hi>mirey Clay,</hi> as to this great <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:57608:28"/> 
               <hi>of the Lord's Supper,</hi> and the Doctrine <hi>of Eating the Fleſh and Drinking the Blood of Chriſt,</hi> out of which it was drawn, and degraded the moſt loſty <hi>Spirituality</hi> of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, into the pooreſt and even vileſt of carnal Apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerning it, in the Doctrine of a <hi>Carnal fleſhly Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. At the ſame Times, and by the ſame Degrees, grew up a <hi>Deſpotick, Arbitrary Church power,</hi> that impoſed what it pleas'd under <hi>Anathemaes, Curſes, Excommunications,</hi> Brands of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> and all Cruelty, upon the Bodies, Names, Eſtates, of thoſe, who even to Syllables did not Say as they Said, and do as they did: while at the ſame Time alſo there Invaded Perſons of as honeſt and ſincere a Devotion as Ignorance could produce, a Veneration for the Name of the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> and the <hi>Governours</hi> of it, and their <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Impreſs, the Stamp of this Authority, being ſet ſo particularly and Imperially upon this Doctrine of <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation,</hi> it is no wonder it prevail'd ſo far, and ſunk ſo deep into the Minds of Men, through what every Age from thoſe Worthies before-nam'd, contributed both to the Groſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Authoritativeneſs of this <hi>falſe Article of Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I forbear, becauſe I would be as inoffenſive as may be conſiſtent with Truth to remark upon that <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> that <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> which the <hi>Apoſtles of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> foretold, were, even then beginning, and to riſe high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and higher in the <hi>Latter Times,</hi> to which even many Things, innocent and inoffenſive in themſelves at firſt, and indeed all Contingencies, <hi>fathally</hi> concurr'd; and which, it is moſt certain, are not yet remov'd. Nor do I think fit at this Time to Animadvert upon the <hi>Covetous Practices,</hi> Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties, and Inhumanities, into which <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> hath been <hi>Tranſubſtantiated,</hi> not only in the true, real ſenſe of <hi>ſpiritual Wickedneſs,</hi> but in a ſenſe as <hi>corporeal</hi> as <hi>Corporeity</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:57608:29"/>
            <p> I haſten therefore to the fifth Head; <hi>viz.</hi> To repreſent to you the Danger of ſuch a Doctrine, as that <hi>Fleſhly Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation,</hi> not ſo much as it is a contemplative Thing, a Notion, a manner of Apprehenſion, or matter of Diſcourſe, though that alſo, but as it carries the Practice of <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Adoration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in theſe Great Points we may very plainly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincingly underſtand the great Danger of that <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The believing it muſt needs ſhake the Credit of all the knowing and judging Faculties of our Natures and Beings, than which, nothing can be more deſtructive to Religion, or put all Things into greater Diſorder and Confuſion, that concern God, our Selves, or our Motions in relation to another World.</p>
            <p>For if our Faculties are not true, we have nothing to guide our ſelves, or to be guided by.</p>
            <p>Now the Faculties of our Minds firſt judge, and act by Senſe, then by Reaſon, then by the Notices or Sentiments of Natural Conſcience, then by Faith; and theſe muſt be all ſound, in due ſtate; They have all their proper Objects, they are all finite, and by theſe Rules they are limited; they muſt not go out of their Limits. It is true, theſe are each as ſo many Stories one above another, and the lower muſt not preſume into the Region of the higher, for then they will be miſtaken, and in Error; yet the higheſt is ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſuſtained by the lower. And ſeeing they all are from God, whatever is true in the loweſt cannot be contradicted in the higheſt; and therefore whatever is pretended in the higheſt, cannot be true there, if it be juſtly denied in the loweſt.</p>
            <p>Now it were eaſie to ſhew, this Notion of Carnal <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation</hi> muſt be falſe in all the judgment of our Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; but I ſhall only inſtance in Senſe: And, if the Bread be Bread in the Judgment of every one of our Senſes, of the Senſes of all Men, in all Places, at all Times, and in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:57608:29"/> all Ages under the moſt advantageous Circumſtances for ſenſe to judge by, the contrary can never be true in Reaſon, in natural Conſcience, nor in Faith; for then, either there muſt be no ſuch Faculty as Senſe, or that fundamental Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of the Souls Judgment by Senſe, muſt be falſe, and ſo all our Faculties will loſe their Credit; for they may be falſe too, ſeeing he that gave us one gave us all of them, and this of Senſe is that we moſt live and act by in this World.</p>
            <p>If any attempt to parallel this with the Doctrine of the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Word,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit, being ONE,</hi> to which, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (ſay they) can never ſubſcribe; the Caſe is manifeſtly different, ſeeing it is certain, our Faculties are finite, and cannot judge of Infinity but by Faith in divine Revelation: Infinite Being is <hi>too High, too Deep, too Broad, too Long,</hi> for <note place="margin">Job 11. 7, 8, 9.</note> a Finite Reaſon to judge of; It is not its proper Object.</p>
            <p>But Colour, Taſte, Figure, Hard, Soft, Sound, may be all judg'd by Senſe, and properly are ſo to be judg'd.</p>
            <p>Or if any ſhould make the ſame Objection againſt that <hi>Spiritual Tranſubſtantiation</hi> we have made out by Scripture, 'tis certain, It is only cogniſable, and to be judg'd of by Faith and Revelation: Senſe hath no Title to judge of it; If it be maintain'd by Faith, it is maintain'd in its proper Court. But it is certain, The Judgment whether this Bread be Bread, or Wine be Wine, is to be made by ſome one or more of the Senſes, at leaſt in the Univerſality of all the Senſes, of all Perſons, Times, Places.</p>
            <p>Let any one then lay that place 1 <hi>Epiſt. John c.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>That which we have heard, that which our Eyes have ſeen, which we have looked upon, and our Hands have handled,</hi> &amp;c. to the being born down, That in theſe Senſes, and all others, we are miſtaken in judging Bread to be Bread when it is no Bread, and Wine, when it is no Wine; Muſt not all the Argument, the Evidence, the Aſſurance the Apoſtle gives, ſtand for nothing? Nay, Muſt not all Scripture-Miracles whatever fall by the ſame ſtroke the Senſes do in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? and Religion be ſuſpected but only Juggle and Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture?
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:57608:30"/> For here Senſe is upon its own Object, in its own Buſineſs: All Senſe that is in the World, agrees; and a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Faith only makes it void.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hereby that great Excellency of Scripture in giving Divine and Spiritual Things under ſenſible, prophetical Events under Emblems, myſtical Things under Types of a material Nature, great, concernful practical Truth under Parables, is made void; for if it may not be allowed it to mean Spirituality under <hi>[This is my Body,]</hi> it may be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it in all Things elſe, ſeeing in nothing it can be more neceſſary, than when all the Senſes in the World bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the neceſſity, and the ſublime Spirituality of the Thing, as we have ſet out, requires it. This muſt needs turn even the minds of Men into groſs and carnal. Muſt not that great Hereſie of the <hi>Anthropomorphites</hi> (as was intimated before) be defended and made good, becauſe Scripture ſpeaks ſpiritual Things freely and under Senſibles; nay, all Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage does the ſame, and is made fooliſh by ſo perverting it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Amuſe and Wonderment of the minds of men, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded of ſuch a <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> muſt needs be great, and their Thoughts gazing after a Nothing, and taken off from the greateſt Buſineſs of a ſpiritual Application to Chriſt according to his Word, and the whole Truth of the Goſpel concerning Redemption by him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But that which is yet the greateſt danger of all, There is nothing the Scripture ſo much abhors, as to bring God into a contemptible, vile, mean Appearance, and that ſuch an Appearance ſhould claim Divine Honour, a ſhare in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Glory. There never was a Divine Appearance, that God requir'd any Acknowledgment of himſelf in, but there was a Retinue of Divine Power and Majeſty with it, to aſſure the minds of men, and to direct them to the Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of God alone.</p>
            <p>When Chriſt was here in the World <hi>under the Form of a Servant,</hi> the Diſguiſe of a <hi>Carpenters Son,</hi> I do not find that there was any Act of Worſhip done to him; but when the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:57608:30"/> 
               <hi>Shecinah,</hi> the Preſence of Glory, deſcended upon him; when the <hi>Wiſe men from the East</hi> worſhipped him in his Infancy, a <hi>Star from Heaven,</hi> as an Evidence of his Divinity, guided them. It is never recorded the Diſciples worſhipped him, but after his Reſurrection, and when they ſaw his <hi>Apotheoſis,</hi> his Aſcenſion, his receiving up into Glory, or when a Ray of his Divinity ſhone out, as in <hi>the Draught of Fiſhes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet it is true, that throughout the Time of his publick <note place="margin">Luke 5. 8.</note> Appearance, though <hi>he was made Fleſh, and dwelt among them,</hi> yet they <hi>beheld his Glory as the Glory of the only Begotten of the Father, full of Grace and Truth,</hi> not bodily, but divine, ſpiritual was the Object of their Worſhip.</p>
            <p>How does God caution and warn the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that <hi>They ſaw no Similitude, no Likeneſs of any thing</hi> when <hi>he ſpake out of the midst of the Fire: They heard a Voice of Words,</hi> but they ſaw no Similitude, <hi>that they might not Copy God out into any ſuch.</hi> Deut. 4. 12. 15, 16.</p>
            <p>If men ſay, They intend to worſhip only the True God in Jeſus Chriſt, in the chang'd Bread; Conſider what miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Preſence, what Evidences of Divinity can you find to ſummon your Worſhip, that you may be ſecure from Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry?</p>
            <p>Conſider what the Glory, what the Majeſty of the Divine Appearances are, when he hath ſummon'd the Worſhip of his Servants; ſome Extraordinaries of Glory have always been the Alarm of their Worſhip.</p>
            <p>One great part of the Idolatry of the Heathens was their courſe Repreſentation of God; <hi>They changed the Glory of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 23. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Incorruptible God into an Image made like to Corruptible Man,</hi> and to Birds, &amp;c. <hi>They changed the Truth of God into a Lye, and worſhipped and ſerved the Creature more than the Creator, Bleſſed for ever,</hi> or beſides, or <hi>miſſing the Creator,</hi> and as <hi>againſt him, Bleſſed for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though I would not therefore ſay, It is Idolatry; yet I heartily pray, Men may not be enſnar'd in ſo great a danger of it: I could wiſh it were not, as the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 1. if
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:57608:31"/> it be lawful to do ſo. I am ſure the Danger is exceeding great of ſtooping God ſo low, and then Worſhipping him as in a piece of Bread.</p>
            <p>There remains nothing now but the laſt Head of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; <hi>viz.</hi> To draw up all into ſhort Inferences, applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory to Practice.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>1</label> I would even put it to the Choice of any wiſe Man, what kind of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> is moſt deſirable, and worthy to be preferr'd; Whether that Inſipid one, at the ſuppos'd Expence of a Miracle, ſo unaccountable to Senſe and Reaſon as chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the Bread and Wine into <hi>the Body and Blood of Chriſt</hi> materially taken, which yet offers nothing to the Senſe to excite and ſtir up the Mind by, to attend upon the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Preſence,</hi> nor contributes any thing to the Soul; Or that ſpiritual <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> which is <hi>All Spirit</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> and certainly <hi>gives Life</hi> to the Soul that Receives it.</p>
            <p>The one can be not ſo much as an outward <hi>Sign,</hi> becauſe not <hi>viſible;</hi> the other is certainly the <hi>inward, inviſible Grace,</hi> that yet demonſtrates it ſelf in all real, viſible Effects, with Demonſtration of the Spirit and Power, and that will raiſe us up at the <hi>last day:</hi> The one does nothing, <hi>For if any man have not the Spirit of Christ, he is none of his;</hi> The other is that very Spirit of Chriſt that is <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs:</hi> ſo that the true Believer, who hath the Spirit of Chriſt, hath the whole Vertue from that within, and the <hi>Bread and Wine</hi> are preſent to the Senſe, by Chriſt himſelf ſanctified, and appointed to do good that way; which nothing unſeen can do, in the very nature of the Thing, any more than in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible can affect Senſe.</p>
            <p>That then which offers not it ſelf to Senſe nor Reaſon, and does no good without the Spirit, and Life receiv'd by Faith, what can it do at all?</p>
            <p>To a Man without Faith, it hath not ſo much as the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Viſibility to ſtir up to Faith by ſenſe; it cannot of it ſelf give the inward Grace neither; ſo that it indeed is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, nor can do any thing. But the <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> of the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:57608:31"/> 
               <hi>Body and Blood of Christ</hi> immediately hath the ſaving Effect upon the true Believer; It Invites the very Unbeliever by its Excellency, while it offers it ſelf under the ſenſible Signs of <hi>Bread and Wine</hi> made Intelligible and Intellectual by the whole Doctrine of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>It is eaſie therefore thus far to know, what is to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen: But on the other ſide, There is the great Danger, if this <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> be a miſtake, (as there is ſo great aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance it is.) There is, for a miſtakes ſake, all the danger imaginable of overthrowing the whole Credit of our Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and of Religion by it, and the greateſt danger of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, againſt the Precept of the <hi>Apoſtle Paul,</hi> upon the very Diſcourſe of the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> a <hi>Prophecy,</hi> I am perſuaded, of Future Danger, as well as an Admonition; <hi>Dearly Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, viz.</hi> Chriſtians, <hi>flee from Idolatry,</hi> the Idolatry which <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 14.</note> turns the <hi>Cup of the Lord,</hi> and the <hi>Table of the Lord,</hi> into a <hi>Cup</hi> and <hi>Table</hi> of, what I am afraid to name; for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is the Author of all <hi>Idolatry.</hi> It is likewiſe againſt the <hi>prophetical</hi> Farewel of the <hi>Apoſtle John,</hi> after declaring the <hi>True God</hi> and <hi>Eternal Life; Little Children, Keep your ſelves from Idols,</hi> 1 Ep. <hi>John</hi> c. <hi>ult.</hi> v. <hi>ult.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When therefore, There is ſo little Gain at the coſt of ſuch a miraculous Power ſuppos'd on God's part, of ſo prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a Faith on ours, and ſo great a danger; what, but a ſtrange Servitude to a <hi>Church,</hi> calling it ſelf <hi>Infallible,</hi> can ſubject us to ſuch an undeſirable Opinion?</p>
            <p n="2">2. It ſhould raiſe us to high Thoughts of the Redemption of Chriſt, thus nearly uniting it ſelf to, and incorporating it ſelf within us: Although it is matter of Faith, yet it is ſo abundantly aſſur'd to that Faculty of our Minds, to Know, and to be aſſur'd to that Faculty of our Minds, to Know, and to be aſſur'd by ſo high a Revelation; that if we purſue it by that Power, that Faculty, ſanctified actually to believe in Chriſt; and that we come to live by that Faith <hi>of the Son of God,</hi> it will be even as certain, as ſenſible, as Life it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:57608:32"/> 3. We ſhould lift up our Souls and Hearts to Chriſt in the Heavens, on the Right-hand of God, Interceeding for us; for there <hi>he ſtill eats the Paſſover,</hi> and drinks of that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>ſame Fruit of the Vine</hi> with us, as it is <hi>new</hi> and <hi>fulfill'd</hi> in his <hi>Fathers Kingdom,</hi> there he continually applies it to our Hearts, as the great Teſtator, and Riſen ſurviving <hi>Surety,</hi> Executor, or <hi>Mediator</hi> of <hi>his own Teſtament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. It ſhould oblige us to a continual Appretiation, and high value of the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> and joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> (if it could be) to every <hi>Lord's Day,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lordly Supper. Lordly Day.</note> to which it is coupled in ſo peculiar, and unparallel'd only to themſelves, a <hi>New-Teſtament-Expreſſion.</hi> For though it hath a conſtant and undividable Annexion to that <hi>New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament,</hi> of which Chriſt hath made it a viſible Sum; altho' it is always preach'd with the Goſpel, and is as it were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred in that Preaching; yet, becauſe the whole Goſpel is preſent, and ſenſibly preach'd in that Sacrament alſo, we ſhould embrace both within our moſt conſcientious Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: And the very Ordinance it ſelf is undoubtedly the moſt ordinary means of a ſuperadditional Aſſurance and Conveyance of the Goſpel-Efficacy into our Hearts, and therefore by no means to be neglected.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It perſuades us to an earneſt Care and Caution againſt violating the great Ordinances of the Goſpel preach'd in both the Word of God, and <hi>in the Lord's Supper;</hi> for it is the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> to be <hi>Eaten</hi> and <hi>Drunk;</hi> and if we neglect and refuſe, or unworthily par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, we are <hi>guilty</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of the <hi>Lord;</hi> we do not <hi>diſcern</hi> and take due notice of the <hi>Lord's Body,</hi> ſo it becomes a <hi>ſavor of Death unto Death</hi> in the <hi>Word,</hi> and of <hi>Judgment</hi> to Condemnation (if we perſevere ſo to do) in the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> becauſe it is a degree of that great Sin of <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy, treading under foot the Son of God, counting the Blood of the Covenant a common thing, doing Injury to the Spirit of Grace, Crucifying him a-freſh, and putting him to an open Shame.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:57608:32"/>
            <p> And when by the ordinary Profeſſion of Jeſus Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Born, and <hi>Baptiz'd</hi> into the only <hi>Holy Religion</hi> in the World, Educated in it, we are <hi>caught in its Net,</hi> and under <hi>the Bond of the Covenant,</hi> the Goſpel is Preach'd to us whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we will or no, and the <hi>Lord's Supper</hi> goes along with it, whether we Hear, or <hi>whether we forbear,</hi> whether we Receive, or whether we forbear, we muſt know, we ſhall know the Goſpel in its Preaching, in the <hi>Lord's Supper</hi> inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable from it, hath been among us. We are All <hi>Baptiz'd</hi> in the <hi>Cloud,</hi> and in the <hi>Sea of the Goſpel Miniſtry,</hi> every way ſurrounding us: We <hi>All Eat the ſame ſpiritual Meat, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Drink the ſame ſpiritual Drink, and that is Christ.</hi> The <hi>Bread broken among us,</hi> the <hi>Cup of Bleſſing bleſs'd among us,</hi> encloſes us, though in regard of Unbelief and Impenitency, we <hi>Eat and Drink Judgment to our ſelves,</hi> and with <hi>many of us God is not well pleaſed,</hi> and <hi>our Carkaſſes will fall</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this <hi>Manna,</hi> this <hi>Water of the Rock</hi> vouchſaf'd to us, if we Repent not.</p>
            <p>There is therefore no way of avoiding the Goſpel-Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but by <hi>Receiving the Lord Jeſus aright,</hi> and <hi>walking in him:</hi> No Abatement of our Danger, as to the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> but by giving no <hi>Sleep to our Eyes,</hi> nor <hi>Slumber to our Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lids,</hi> till we have brought our ſelves into an approved ſtate for it. Refuſal of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> in its Preaching, in the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> will not be ſo Tollerable as <hi>Sodom's Judgment:</hi> There is no Safety any way, but in <hi>Eating and Drinking Christ,</hi> ſo that we may live for ever; elſe we can <hi>have no life</hi> in us.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Seeing all the <hi>Goſpel</hi> and <hi>Lord's Supper</hi> hath ſuch rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Laſt Day, to the <hi>Table of Christ in his Kingdom,</hi> in his Glory, and to Eating and Drinking then in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, let us <hi>lift up our Heads,</hi> our Thoughts, our Deſires, our Prayers, to it: Although theſe Ordinances ought to be all our Delights on Earth, yet they are but the State below, a State of the Delay, and <hi>Patience of Chriſt for his Kingdom; A ſhewing forth the Lord's Death till he come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
